<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached to the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament at their pvbliqve fast, Novem. 17, 1640 by Cornelius Burges.</title>
            <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 172 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5683</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19994</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12676442</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12676442</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65562</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65562)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 681:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached to the Honourable House of Commons assembled in Parliament at their pvbliqve fast, Novem. 17, 1640 by Cornelius Burges.</title>
                  <author>Burges, Cornelius, 1589?-1665.</author>
                  <author>Marshall, Stephen, 1594?-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 58 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Badger, for P. Stephens and C. Meredith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Cornelius Burges, Stephen Marshall.</note>
                  <note>Also published as the first sermon in his Two sermons ... London, 1641.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Fast-day sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65562:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED TO the Honourable Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT. AT THEIR PVBLIQVE <hi>FAST,</hi> NOVEM. 17. 1640. By <hi>Cornelius Burges</hi> D. D.</p>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order_to_print">
                  <body>
                     <p>Publiſhed by <hi>Order</hi> of that <hi>Houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. Badger,</hi> for <hi>P. Stephens,</hi> and <hi>C. Meredith,</hi> at the Gilded LION in Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> CHURCH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>YARD. 1641.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65562:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65562:2"/>
            <head>TO THE HONOVRABLE HOVSE OF COMMONS now Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen firſt it pleaſed <hi>You</hi> to require our ſervice in Preaching <hi>at Your</hi> late Publike <hi>Faſt,</hi> we reſolved to cloſe our eyes againſt all Clouds of diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ariſing from our owne unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſse and inſufficiency, and to ſet our ſelves wholly to ſeek what the Lord would command us to deliver in his Name, at ſuch a time, to ſuch an Honourable and awfull Aſsembly, with a totall deniall of our ſelves.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 82.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And albeit we ſhould have beene glad to have beene ſpared this expoſing of our ſelves to the publike view; yet, <hi>You</hi> appointing otherwiſe, we hold it equall that the joynt <hi>entreaty</hi> of the <hi>Repreſentative Body</hi> of the whole <hi>Communalty</hi> of the kingdome ſhould bee regarded, and have choſen rather that others ſhould cenſure us of <hi>weakeneſſe,</hi> than <hi>You</hi> ſhould charge
<pb facs="tcp:65562:3"/> us with <hi>Diſobedience:</hi> Your <hi>Requeſt</hi> being no leſſe than a <hi>command;</hi> and <hi>Your</hi> acceptance ſufficient to give value to things of themſelves both meane and worthleſſe.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, according to our Duty ſo willingly as the conſciouſneſſe of our ſlender performances would permit, we obey Your <hi>Order,</hi> and doe now, although ſomewhat late, humbly offer theſe two plaine Sermons (for, who expects other in a <hi>Faſt?</hi>) at the footſtoole of <hi>Your Tribunall,</hi> as a laſting Monument of Our Gratitude for <hi>Your</hi> encouraging <hi>Approbation</hi> of, and ſolemne <hi>Thankes</hi> for our weake endeavours in the preaching of them.</p>
            <p>If in ſome places wee have taken that juſt liberty which all others have done before us, we truſt it ſhall not be imputed; ſo long as in the most materiall paſſages we have kept to the very words which at firſt we uſed, ſo farre as was neceſſary; and have not wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingly ſwerved an haires bredth from the ſenſe and ſubſtance in the reſidue.</p>
            <p>Wee have indeed pared off ſome Repetitions, which in ſpeaking had their uſe, the more to inculcate, and the better to ſet on the matter, but would not have been ſo gratefull in Writing, becauſe Readers account every thing too long that hath any thing too much. We have
<pb facs="tcp:65562:3"/> likewiſe contracted ſome expreſſions, which in diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of ſo much length, could hardly be ſo conciſe as we deſired, Memory being not alwaies at hand to give birth to every Conception of our minds in ſuch formes as wee intended. And ſome few things we have added, where ſtraites of time, or defect of memory made ſome balkes in the firſt delivery.</p>
            <p>What ever our performances be, we humbly leave them in Your hands, and under Your Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, which we are bold to expect, becauſe they are by Your own Act drawne from us, and that in a time ſo queaſie and diſtempered as can hardly beare that food, or Phyſik which is needfull for it. Seldome <hi>doth a wiſe Reproofe,</hi> a neceſſary <hi>Exhortation,</hi> or wholſome <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> meet with an <hi>obedient Eare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The God of Heaven ſteere all Your weighty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations by his own Counſell, to his own Glory; cover <hi>You</hi> ſtill under his own Wing, and make You the most <hi>accompliſht,</hi> beſt <hi>united,</hi> and moſt <hi>ſucceſſefull</hi> and <hi>glorious houſe of Commons</hi> that ever ſate in that <hi>High Court;</hi> but chiefly in the effectuall endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a further Sanction of, and ſtronger Guard about our true <hi>Palladium,</hi> the true <hi>Religion,</hi> already eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed among us; in the perfecting of the <hi>Reformation</hi> of it; in the erecting, maintaining, protecting, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging
<pb facs="tcp:65562:4"/> of an able, godly, faithfull, zealous, profitable, Preaching<note n="*" place="margin">This was our joynt &amp; earneſt ſuit to You, in Preaching; and we now again <hi>beſeech</hi> You to ſet your hearts and hands to this <hi>work,</hi> as <hi>Benhail, Obadiah</hi> and other <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in <hi>Iudah</hi> did. 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 17.7, 8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>Miniſtery,</hi> in every Pariſh Church and Chappell throughout England and Wales; and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceding to the Kings ſacred Majeſty for the ſetting up of a Faithfull, Iudicious, and Zealous <hi>Magiſtracy,</hi> where yet the ſame is wanting, to be ever at hand to back ſuch a <hi>Miniſtery:</hi> without either of which, not only the <hi>power of Godlines</hi> will ſoone degenerate in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>formality,</hi> and <hi>zeale</hi> into Lukewarmeneſſe; but, <hi>Popery, Arminianiſm, Socinianiſme, Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Apoſtacy,</hi> and <hi>Atheiſme</hi> it ſelfe will more and more croud in upon us, and prevaile against us, doe <hi>You</hi> all <hi>You</hi> can by all other meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now, commending You to God and to the Word of his grace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32.</note> 
               <hi>which is able to build</hi> You <hi>up further, and to give You an inheritance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all them which be ſanctified;</hi> and theſe our Labours to his further bleſſing, whereby all may ſpeedily be brought under the line of his <hi>Covenant,</hi> which is our <hi>ſafety;</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Summe of both Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</note> that he may <hi>continue</hi> with us, which is our <hi>Glory; and we with him,</hi> which is <hi>our happineſſe:</hi> we reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours, moſt devoted to the ſervice of Your Faith in all Dutie,</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>Cornelius Burges.</item>
                     <item>Stephen Marſhall.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:65562:4"/>
            <head>THE FIRST SERMON, at the late Faſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this Preface was uſed, before the TEXT was read.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat great Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> when he had to doe with wiſe men, held it a point of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to paſse by ſome things which hee would not have wayved among meaner capacities. His practiſe ſhall be now my preſident.</p>
            <p>This Honourable Aſſembly having deſigned mee to beare ſo great a ſhare in this weightie Worke, I hold it my duty to conſider, that, how weake and unworthy ſo ever I my ſelfe be, yet I am now to <hi>ſpeake to Wiſe Men,</hi> who need not ſo much to be Catechiſed touching the <hi>Nature,</hi> as to be incited and quickned to the principall <hi>Vſe</hi> of a Religious <hi>Faſt,</hi> which conſiſteth not ſolely in ſuch drawing neere to God by extraordinary Prayer and Humiliation as may produce a totall divorce from our deerest Lusts, but alſo (and that more principally) in a particular, formall, ſolemne, entire engaging and binding of our ſelves, by an indiſſoluble <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> to that God whoſe face and favour we ſeeke, and implore.</p>
            <p>And this I apprehend to be a ſubject more neceſſary, by how much this dutie appeares to be leſse heeded and regarded by the greater number of the choyceſt Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>For, as it too often falls out, even among the best, in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipating that ſacred and dreadfull Ordinance of the Lords
<pb facs="tcp:65562:5"/> 
               <hi>SUPPER,</hi> (whereof alſo we are ſhortly to communicate) that mo labor more to <hi>diſcerne,</hi> and <hi>feed</hi> upon his bleſſed Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and bloud, ſpiritually by faith, to make Chriſt their owne, (which muſt be done too) than actually, totally, and abſolutely (then) to devote, reſigne, and yeeld up themſelves unto him, in the act of receiving, <hi>to be his ſervants:</hi> So it doth not ſeldome happen in the exerciſe of holy <hi>Faſting,</hi> that not a few of that ſmall handfull which deſire to approach the preſence of God in truth, are more converſant in ſearching, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsing, bewailing of ſin, and in craving for mercy, (all of which are neceſſary duties) than in working up their hearts to that in diſpenſable pitch of heavenly reſolution, ſincerely to ſtrike through a religious and inviolable <hi>Covenant</hi> with their <hi>God.</hi> Whereas without this, all their labour will be utterly loſt, their expectations fruſtrate, they take the glorious Name of God in vaine, provoke the eyes of his glory more againſt them, cauſing him infinitely to loath and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate both their perſons, and ſervice; nor ſhall they ever, by all their crying and ſighing, no not by whole rivers of teares, be able to draw downe an arme of Mercy from Heaven to come and ſave them.</p>
            <p>The more effectually therefore to provoke both my ſelfe and you at this time, to the due performance of this moſt neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (but moſt neceſſary) dutie, I have thought fit, in a very plaine and familiar way ſutable to the nature of this exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe (which ought to be as ſerious, as ſolemne) to worke and chafe into all our hearts the ſtrength and ſpirit of that good Word of God, which you ſhall finde written for our inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65562:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The Propheſie of the Prophet</hi> Ieremiah, <hi>Chap. 50. V. 5.</hi> They ſhall aske the way to Zion with their faces thitherward, <hi>ſaying,</hi> Come, and let us joyne our ſelves unto the Lord in an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that ſhall not be forgotten.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hich words are part of a Prophecy (terrible to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> but comfortable to the Church) uttered,<note place="margin">The <hi>Intro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction</hi> to the maine <hi>Diſcourſe.</hi>
               </note> and penned by the Prophet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> about the fourth yeere both of the <hi>Babyloniſh captivity,</hi> and of the tributa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reigne of <hi>Zedekiah.</hi> The occaſion, this.</p>
            <p>The Prophet having laboured about thirtie yeeres, to humble Iudah by continually ringing in her eares the dolefull tydings of a ſore captivity approaching, could not bee beleeved. But, when once the quicke and ſad ſenſe of their bondage under the Caldean Yoke had forced from them an acknowledgement of the truth of his Propheſies, he found it as hard a taske to worke their hearts to any hope of deliverance. For, as it is a worke even inſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perable, to poſſeſſe a people ripe for deſtruction, that any evill is neere them, till the wrath of God breake in upon them and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelme them; ſo is it a buſineſſe of little leſſe difficultie to hold up the ſpirits even of Gods owne people, once caſt under any great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, with any hope of reſcue.</p>
            <p>This was <hi>Iudah</hi> caſe. Before the Babylonian had laid this yoke on their necks, God had plainly revealed, and often inculcated that it ſhould lye upon them juſt 70. yeares and no longer,<note place="margin">Ier. 25.11, 29.10.</note> after which they ſhould have liberty of return to their own Land again. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit, the weight of their miſery, the abſence of God, (who had <hi>caſt them out of his ſight</hi>) together with the inſolence and cruelty of their proud oppreſſors, had throwne them down ſo low in a diſconſolate condition, that nothing which God could either now ſay or doe, was ſufficient to raiſe up their hearts to any aſſurance of returne. The ſame ſtrength which Luſt hath to draw men from obedience, it will ſurely have afterwards to drive men from beleeving, in their greateſt neceſſities of <hi>living by faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The maine beame which ſtucke in their eyes to hinder their ſight of deliverance promiſed, was, the greateneſſe and invincible poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65562:6"/> of the Chaldean Monarchy (then in her pride) and more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the ſtrength of <hi>Babylon</hi> the Queene and Miſtreſſe of that puiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Empire.<note place="margin">Introducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> How could they hope to be delivered, when ſhe that commanded the world detained them? <hi>Shall the prey be taken from the Mighty,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſay 49.24.</note> 
               <hi>or the lawfull captive delivered?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To cure them therefore of this deſperate deſponſion of mind, the Lord ſtirred up this Prophet to foretell the totall and finall ſubverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and ruine of <hi>Babylon</hi> and of that whole Monarchy; and further, to declare from God, that the deſolation thereof ſhould be the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the captivity of <hi>Iudah</hi> in it. The better to aſſure them of all this, <hi>Ieremiah</hi> wrote the whole Prophecy againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> (con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in this Chapter and the next following) in a Book by it ſelfe, which he ſent to <hi>Babylon</hi> by the hand of <hi>Seraiah</hi> (Lord Chamber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine to <hi>Zedekiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 51.59.</note> and now going in an Embaſſie from his Maſter to great <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi>) with Command from the Prophet, that, after the reading thereof to the captives, he ſhould <hi>binde a ſtone unto it, and caſt it into the midſt of Euphrates,</hi> with this ſaying pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced over it, <hi>Thus ſhall Babylon ſinke, and ſhall not riſe, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to haſten to my Text, In the five firſt verſes of this Chapter, the Prophet ſummarily compriſeth the ſubſtance of his whole Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy againſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> declaring, 1. her <hi>deſtruction,</hi> 2. the <hi>Meanes,</hi> 3. the conſequent thereof to the people of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> And firſt, he makes Proclamation, and an <hi>Oiyes!</hi> as it were, to all the world, to come and behold the Great Worke he was to doe againſt <hi>Babylon</hi> the chiefe Citie of the Empire, againſt <hi>Bell</hi> the chiefe Idoll of that Citie, and againſt <hi>Merodach</hi> the glory both of that Citie and Empire; yea, though the King then reigning when God meant to deſtroy it, ſhould prove as potent as that great King, the firſt of that name, who for reſtoring the declining Empire to her ancient Splendor, and for tranſlating the Imperiall Seat from <hi>Nineve</hi> to <hi>Babylon,</hi> was by poſterity worſhipped as a God, and transferred his name to all his ſucceſſors, as the name of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to the Egyptian Kings, of <hi>Benhadad</hi> to the Syrian Monarchs, and of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to the Roman Emperours. Although all theſe ſhould be joyned together to withſtand the downfall of that Monarchy, yet deſolation ſhould be brought over them all, they ſhould all be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded and removed for ever, <hi>Verſe</hi> 1.2. and all to make way for the deliverance of the Church.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:65562:6"/>
            <p>But what ſhould bee the <hi>meanes</hi> of ſuch an unexpected deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? This was to bee done by an Army from the <hi>North,</hi> that is, by the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> both of which, but more eſpecially the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Medes,</hi> were ſituated towards the <hi>North</hi> from <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Omne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum ab Aquilone.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ominous. That theſe were the men, appeares more fully by their deſcription in the reſidue of this, and of the 51. Chap. This Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therne Army ſhould bee the confuſion of <hi>Babylon,</hi> the confuſion of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhould prove the reſtoring of the Church (<hi>ver.</hi> 3.) And the reſtoring of the Church ſhould produce a <hi>Covenant</hi> with God.</p>
            <p>For, behold, the iſſue and <hi>conſequent</hi> of the ruine of <hi>Babylon</hi> was, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the returne of the captive Iewes, from thence to Ieruſalem, and a renewing Covenant with him that had ſhewed ſuch mercy on them, <hi>verſ</hi> 4.5.</p>
            <p>For, <hi>in thoſe dayes, and in that time, ſaith the Lord, the children of Iſrael ſhall come, they and the children of Iudah together, going and wee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, they ſhall goe and ſeeke the Lord their God. They ſhall aske the way to Zion with their faces thitherward, ſaying, Come and let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> This began to be fulfilled at the end of ſeventy yeeres determined, when the Empire was firſt over-runne and ſubdued by <hi>Cyrus</hi> the <hi>Perſian.</hi> For he made Proclamation of libertie to returne,<note place="margin">2 Chr. 36.22</note> in the firſt yeere of his Raigne. And when they returned, this was their deportment; they went weeping; and, <hi>to ſeeke the Lord their God.</hi> They <hi>goe,</hi> not ſo much to repoſſeſſe their ancient patrimony and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, and to grow rich in the world, as to ſeeke and finde the Lord their God, and that with a reſolution to enter into <hi>Covenant</hi> with Him, and ſuch a Covenant as ſhould never <hi>bee forgotten,</hi> but daily remembred and carefully performed.</p>
            <p>You now ſee the Context. Should I now divide the Text,<note place="margin">Actus.</note> I might ſhew you here.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, an <hi>Act,</hi> expreſſed by their induſtry, in ſetting upon a long and tedious journey to Zion. <hi>They ſhall aske the way to Zion.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, the <hi>manner</hi> how they manage this journey,<note place="margin">Modus.</note> it is
<list>
                     <item>1. With all <hi>intention of ſpirit,</hi> they aske the way to Zion, <hi>with their faces thitherward.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. With fervent <hi>charity</hi> towards, and mutuall <hi>zeale</hi> for each other, to quicken and inflame one another to the ſame work, <hi>ſaying, Come.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:65562:7"/>
               <item>Thirdly, the end of their journey, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> (with ſo much intention of ſpirit and inflamed charity, calling and crying to one another in ſuch a manner,<note place="margin">FINIS.</note>) they ſet upon; all was for this: <hi>Let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant</hi> that <hi>ſhal not be forgotten</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>I might eaſily alſo caſt out theſe generals of the Text into many leſſer branches: but it is not now a time to trifle, or to play with a Text. Yea, I ſhall not diſtinctly proſecute all the parts already laid out, but (as the duty of this day requireth) inſiſt rather upon that which is the maine, and bring in the other as ſubordinate thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, by occaſion afterwards, in explication of the principall point. For we ſee troopes in the Text bound for <hi>Zion;</hi> and, ſo haſty <hi>thither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward,</hi> that they <hi>ſalute not any man by the way,</hi> nor ſo much as looke aſide any way: they goe <hi>with their faces thitherward:</hi> all the ſtay they make, is but to call others along with them, and amongſt theſe, us, ſaying, <hi>Come.</hi> And, what is the buſineſſe; the end of all this haſt? Nothing but this, <hi>Let us joyne our ſelves unto the Lord in an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Covenant, &amp;c.</hi> This, how ever it were laſt in execution, yet was it firſt in their intention, in the undertaking of this journey, and therefore now muſt be principally inſiſted upon.</p>
            <p>You ſee here a people looſed from the Babyloniſh captivitie, and returning to <hi>Zion:</hi> and, in their returne to have this in their hearts, in their mouthes, and in their endeavours, namely, upon the receipt of this mercy, to make ſpeed to their God, to enter into a new Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract and ſolemne Covenant with him. So that now the chiefe, and only point of inſtruction which I ſhall recommend to, and preſſe upon you, and mine owne heart with you, is plainly this, that</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The maine <hi>Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> or <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>When God vouchſafes any deliverance to his Church, eſpecially from Babylon, then is it moſt ſeaſonable and moſt neceſſary to cloſe with God by a more ſolemne, ſtrict, and inviolable Covenant to bee his, and only his for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In proſecuting this point (wherein I reſolve to be plaine, and in earneſt) I ſhall firſt ſhew you the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of it, <hi>that it is ſo.</hi> Next, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, if you will, <hi>how and in what manner</hi> this muſt be done. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>grounds</hi> and reaſons of it: and ſo proceed to the <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">i. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>quod ſit.</hi> That it is ſo,</note>For the firſt, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that it is ſo, this will appeare, 1. More ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, upon receipt of any deliverance. 2. More ſpecially, upon an deliverance from <hi>Babylon</hi> above all other.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:65562:7"/>
            <p n="1">1. In generall,<note place="margin">1. <hi>That it is ſo,</hi> in the generall Proved. 1. More ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally.</note> that this uſe muſt be made of any deliverance, appeares both by precept, and example in holy Scripture. We ſhall carry them along together.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. you ſhall finde <hi>Moſes</hi> requiring the people to enter into a <hi>ſpeciall Covenant</hi> with God, <hi>beſide the ſolemne Covenant which he made with them (and they with him) in Horeb.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod. 19.5. &amp;c.</note> To induce them thereunto, <hi>Moſes</hi> refreſheth their memory with the repetition or repreſentation of the many deliverances God had given unto them, out of <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The firſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which they paſſed into, was after their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance out of Egypt. Verſ. 1.</note> and in the wilderneſſe by the ſpace of fortie yeeres, together with the wonders and miracles which he daily wrought for them. And in the ſeventh <hi>ver.</hi> he tels them, that <hi>when ye came into this place</hi> (that is, into <hi>the Land of Moab) Sihon the King of Heſhbon, &amp; Og the King of Baſhan, came cut againſt us unto battell,</hi> &amp;c. What then? Here is deliverance upon deliverance, and the infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is, <hi>Keep therefore the words of this Covenant, and do them,</hi> verſe 9. But, that is the Covenant on Gods part, you will ſay? True,<note place="margin">A ſecond Covenant, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fortie yeeres after the firſt, when they came neere to Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan and ſhortly after were to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into it.</note> but that is not all. He therefore preſſeth them to an actuall perſonall Covenant on their parts, and that upon conſideration of ſo many deliverances. This was his maine buſineſſe with them at the Lords own command. Therefore in <hi>verſ.</hi> 10. he thus beſpeaks them, <hi>Ye stand this day all of you before the Lord your God, your Captaines of your tribes, your Elders, and your Officers, with all the men of Iſrael, your little ones, your wives, and thy ſtranger that is in thy Campe, from the hewer of thy wood to the drawer of thy water, that thou ſhouldſt enter into Covenant with the Lord thy God, and into his Oath which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day.</hi> And in <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. he addeth. <hi>Neither with you onely do I make this Covenant, and this oath, but with him that ſtandeth here with us this day before the Lord our God, and alſo with him that is not here with us this day.</hi> Thus you ſee a Covenant required, ſtricken, and ratified by ſolemne Oath of God and his people mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to one another: they binde themſelves by ſolemne Oath to him, as he by oath had bound himſelf to them. Thus then it was in the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> No eminent deliverance went before, but a ſolemne Covenant followed after.<note n="*" place="margin">As Moſes drew the people, into a Covenant before their entrance into Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an; ſo did Ioſhua alſo, after they were poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of it, Ioſh. 24.25.26. So did Iehoiada, upon the deliverance of Iudah from the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of that bloudy monſter Athaliah, 2 King. 11.17.</note> And, To ſweare a Covenant, is no new device, no humane invention, nor arbitrary Action.</p>
            <p>I will give you but one inſtance more (among many) of this kinde, and it is that of <hi>Aſa,</hi> that good and religious King of <hi>Iudah.</hi> When <hi>Zerah</hi> the Ethiopian infeſted his kingdome with an huge
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65562:8"/> army,<note place="margin">1. <hi>That it is ſo,</hi> in the general.</note> even 1000000, and 300 Chariots, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14. <hi>Aſa</hi> falls to praying, God heard him; they joyned battell, <hi>Aſa</hi> obtained the victory, and <hi>carried away very much ſpoile.</hi> What was the iſſue? Another <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For, in <hi>Chap.</hi> 15 you ſhall finde that preſently upon this, God addreſſeth a Prophet to <hi>Aſa, (Azariah</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Oded</hi>) to tell him and the people, <hi>The Lord is with you while ye be with him.</hi> And, to encourage them to cloſe with God, he addes, in <hi>verſe.</hi> 7. <hi>Be ye ſtrong therefore, and let not your hands be weake: for your worke ſhall be rewarded.</hi> They muſt not onely worke for God, but be <hi>strong</hi> to his worke; and that they might be ſo, there was no way like to that of entring into a <hi>Covenant</hi> with him. For, ſo <hi>Aſa</hi> underſtood it, as appeares by the next words, where it is ſaid, <hi>Aſa, when he heard theſe words,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chron. 14.</note> 
               <hi>tooke courage;</hi> and, although he had before done much in purging the Cities of Iudah of Idolatry, and Idols, of high pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Images, and groves, yet now he goes on to a more thorough reformation, and <hi>put away</hi> the remainder of <hi>abominable Idols out of all the land of Iudah and Benjamin, and out of the Cities which he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Mount Ephraim, and renewed the Altar of the Lord;</hi> for ever where Idols goe up, Gods Altars goe downe, therefore he pulleth downe the one, and ſetteth up the other.</p>
            <p>And not this alone, but he offered unto the Lord a great <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> and both himſelfe and his people <hi>entred into a Covenant to ſeeke the Lord God of their fathers, with all their heart, and with all their ſoule, that whoſoever would not ſeeke the Lord God of Iſrael, ſhould be put to death, whether ſmall or great, whether man or woman; and they ſware unto the Lord with a loud voice, and with ſhouting, and with trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets, and with Cornets.</hi> And all this, immediately upon the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance and victory which he had obtained: for, in <hi>verſe.</hi> 11. it is ſaid expreſſely, that <hi>they offered unto the Lord, the ſame time</hi> (or, <hi>in that very day</hi>) of <hi>the spoile which they had brought,</hi> 700. <hi>Oxen, and</hi> 7000. <hi>Sheepe;</hi> meaning of thoſe, which they had carried away from the Ethiopians that came out to battell againſt them.</p>
            <p>So that now you ſee another ſolemne <hi>Covenant</hi> entred into, not by <hi>Aſa</hi> alone, but by all the people of God, a Covenant ſolemnized in publique by <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> by <hi>Oath,</hi> and under the higheſt penalty of <hi>death</hi> it ſelfe to all that ſhould not obſerve it.</p>
            <p>In purſuit of which Covenant, ſee what he preſently did, He ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65562:8"/> not his owne Mother that regarded it not. For, when he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived that, notwithſtanding this Covenant, the Queene his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Maacha,</hi> would needs retaine her puppet Gods ſtill, and (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the reſt) one abominable Idol, in a grove, ſo obſcene as it is not fit to be named: (<hi>Abulenſis</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In 3. Reg. 15. qs. 11. The Vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar hath it in the Text, ne eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet Princeps in Sacris. Priapi. yea, Lyra is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remptory for this in loc.</note> obſerveth that it was <hi>Priapus,</hi> and conjectureth thence, that ſhee was not only a groſſe Idolatreſſe, but an abominable ſtrumpet: for, ordinarily,<note n="b" place="margin">Hom. againſt peril of Idol. par. 3. Rom. 1.21, 22, 23, 24. &amp;c. wiſ. 14.23 &amp;c. to v. 28. Minut. Faelix in octavi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Athan. orat. cont. Idol. Tertull. in apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. c. 15. B. Hall contempl. in Aſa. Lorinus in Levit. 18. p. 536. Idem in Num. 16. pa. 572 Alii<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> complu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</note> Idolatry and adulte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, ſpirituall and bodily fornication goe together) It is ſaid, that <hi>he removed her from being Queene, becauſe ſhee had made an Idol in a grove, and Aſa cut downe her Idol, and ſtampt it, and burnt it at the brooke Kidron, verſe</hi> 16. Which paſſage is expreſt with an emphaſis in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 15.11. <hi>Alſo Maacha his Mother, even Her, he removed from being Queene.</hi> Although a <hi>Queene,</hi> although a <hi>Mother,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Some ſuppoſe her to have bin his Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, others ſay ſhe was his own Mother, of the ſame name with his Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is more probable, becauſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſtiles her ſo.</note> yet <hi>even her</hi> he depoſed from her dignity.</p>
            <p>This he did, and this he muſt doe, not onely by reaſon of that vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary Covenant into which he had entred, but by vertue of the ſpeciall Command of God himſelfe, in what ever relation ſhee had ſtood unto him. Yea, in <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.6. the Law was more ſtrict, for though ſhee had beene neerer than a Mother, even the <hi>wife of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome,</hi> yet if ſhee were an Idolater, and ſhould <hi>entiſe him ſecretly, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, let us goe and ſerve other Gods,</hi> ſhe muſt have <hi>beene put to death,</hi> and <hi>his owne hand muſt have beene firſt upon her,</hi> verſ. 9.</p>
            <p>You now ſee the point proved in the generall that thus it is with Gods people; upon any notable deliverance,<note n="“" place="margin">Yea ſomtimes upon conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods Iudgements felt or feared. 2 Ch. 29.10. 2 Ch. 34.31, 32. 2. <hi>In ſpeciall.</hi>
               </note> they enter anew in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>ſolemne</hi> and ſtrict <hi>Covenant</hi> with God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. But more eſpecially ought this to be the care of the Church, when God gives her deliverance out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> out of that ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and bondage which of all other was moſt heavy, and lay lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt on her. See this in ſome inſtances, both on Gods part ayming at this in giving deliverance, and on his peoples part performing this after deliverance from <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On Gods part, firſt, This was foreſhewed under the ſimilitude of the basket of <hi>good figs,</hi> Ier. 24.5. There it is ſaid by <hi>the Lord, the God of Iſrael, like theſe good figs ſo will I acknowledge them that are carried away captive of Judah, whom I have ſent out of this place into the land of the Chaldeans for their good: for I will ſet mine eyes upon them for good, and I will bring them againe to this land,</hi> &amp;c And, in the ſeventh verſe it followeth, <hi>I will give them an heart to know me, that I am the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65562:9"/> Lord, and I will be their God: for they ſhall returne unto me with their whole heart.</hi> He will give them an heart to <hi>know</hi> him, to returne, and become his <hi>people,</hi> which cannot be without a <hi>Covenant.</hi> Againe,</p>
            <p>That this is that which Gods heart is exceedingly ſet upon, and full of, namely, that he never meant to bring his people backe from <hi>Babylon,</hi> but upon this very condition (albeit it was a great while ere it was done, and therefore they thrived accordingly, as we ſhall ſhew anon) will yet further appeare by many other paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Prophecy of <hi>Jeremy,</hi> to paſſe by ſundry other Propheſies uttered by <hi>Iſaiah, Micah,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>In <hi>Ier.</hi> 30 18. we ſhall finde a Propheſie, that this ſhould bee done, (and I ſhall ſhew, by and by, that it was afterwards perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>I will bring againe the captivity of Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs tents, and have mercy on his dwelling places,</hi> &amp;c. and in verſ. 21. <hi>I will cauſe him to draw neere, and he ſhall approach unto me;</hi> and then, as one aſſured of it, and admiring at it, he preſently ads; <hi>for who is this that engaged his heart to approach unto me, ſaith the Lord?</hi> That is, both Governour and people, all of them ſhould binde and engage themſelves, (not their outward man alone, but even their very heart and ſoule alſo) by ſolemne Covenant to be the Lords. That this was the meaning, is cleare by the next verſe, <hi>Ye ſhall be my people, and I will be your God.</hi> For it was ſuch an <hi>engaging of their hearts,</hi> as that <hi>one ſhould ſay, I am the Lords; and another ſhall can himſelfe by the name of Iacob: and another ſhall ſubſcribe with his hand unto the Lord, and ſirname himſelfe by the name of Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ver. 31. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Jſa.</hi> 44.5.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ier. 31.</note>So againe, the Lord having firſt promiſed to bring back the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity, he ſubjoynes; <hi>Behold, The dayes come, ſaith the Lord, that I will make a new Covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, &amp; with the houſe of Iudah: not according to the Covenant which I made with their fathers, in the day that I took him out of the Land of Egypt, which my Covenant they brok, although I was an husband unto them ſaith the Lord. But this ſhall be the Covenant that I will make with the houſe of Iſrael; after thoſe days, ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi> Here is a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, God begins the work, but his people follow. They imbrace the Covenant, and joyne themſelves by mutuall Covenant to him. He puts his Law into their hearts, for this very purpoſe.</p>
            <p>Once more. In <hi>Ier.</hi> 32.37. there is a promiſe that God would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65562:9"/> gather his people out of all Countries whither he had caſt them in his wrath, and that he would bring them back to their owne place, and cauſe them to dwell ſafely. He preſently addes this as the product of that mercy; <hi>they ſhall be my people, and I wil be their God, and I will give them one heart, and one way, that they may feare me for ever,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I will make an everlaſting Covenant with them, that I will not turne away from them to doe them good, but I will put my feare in their hearts that they ſhall not depart from me:</hi> Which words goe no leſſe than a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne Covenant mutually made and ſtrucken betweene GOD and His people.</p>
            <p>Thus then you ſee, many plaine and pregnant places of Scripture ſhew, that the maine thing God on his part aymed at, and expected from his people in delivering them from <hi>Babylon,</hi> was, the firme and ſolemne tying and engaging of themſelves by a formall and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Covenant to him, and the <hi>remembring</hi> and keeping of it better than formerly they had done.</p>
            <p>But, ſecondly, all theſe were but propheſies ſhewing what God foreſhewed ſhould be. Will you therefore ſee the thing acted, and all theſe promiſes fulfilled? True it is indeed that the people did not on their parts performe this, they entred not into ſuch a ſolemne Covenant, ſo ſoone as deliverance was by <hi>Cyrus</hi> proclaimed; and they ſped accordingly. <hi>Zorobabel</hi> went indeed before, in the firſt yeere of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and laid the foundation of the Lords Houſe: but we read of no Covenant then made. Therefore, the worke was ſtayed, and the building not finiſhed in an 100 yeeares after, ſay the beſt Chronologers.</p>
            <p>Then comes <hi>Ezra,</hi> and makes ſome reformation of manners; and not onely ſo, but ſome Covenant he and the people entred into, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. But that was but in a particular caſe (and it would be thought a ſtrange one, to this age eſpecially, ſhould it now be preſſed;) there were many that had treſpaſſed againſt their God by taking ſtrange wives of the people of the Land (that worſhipped not the ſame God.) Such therefore, as now were duely touched with the ſence of this ſinne, deſire <hi>Ezra</hi> that a ſolemne <hi>Covenant</hi> might now be made with God, <hi>to put away all</hi> ſuch <hi>wives, and ſuch as were borne of them,</hi> Verſ. 3. Now in the fifth verſe, we ſhall finde this executed. For, <hi>Ezra aroſe, and made the chiefe Prieſts, the Levites, and all Iſrael to ſweare that they ſhould do according to this word, and they ſware.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65562:10"/>
            <p>This was ſomewhat, but not enough: a partiall Covenant, and ſuch as came ſhort of that intended in my Text. You ſhall ſee it more throughly performed afterwards, in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time. For, after <hi>Ezra,</hi> came <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and he makes a more thorough Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; not of mens manners onely, but even of Religion alſo. He ſet up the Ordinances of God in their purity, and tooke care in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular for the preaching of the Word. After all this, he and all the people entred into a ſolemne Covenant, and that at the time of a publique Faſt. And this brings it home to the buſineſſe we are now about. For, as they entred into Covenant upon receipt of ſuch a deliverance, ſo they did it at the time of a ſolemne Faſt. This will appeare throughout the whole ninth Chapter of <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> where it is firſt ſaid, that <hi>the Children of Iſrael were aſſembled with faſting, and with ſack-cloath, and with earth upon them: they ſeparated them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from ſtrangers, they ſtood and confeſſed their ſinnes, and the iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of their fathers.</hi> They juſtified God in all his proceedings againſt them, and in all the evils he had brought upon them. They acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leged that neither they, their Princes, people, or fathers had kept the Law; they had not ſerved God in that kingdom he had beſtowed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſay they, v. 36. <hi>we are ſervants this day, and for the land that thou gaveſt unto our fathers, to eate the fruit thereof, and the good thereof, behold we are ſervants in it, And it yeeldeth much encreaſe unto the Kings whom thou haſt ſet over us, becauſe of our ſinnes: alſo they have dominion over our bodies, and over our cattell at their pleaſure, and we a e in great diſtreſſe. And becauſe of all this, we make a ſure Covenant,</hi> (in the laſt verſe) <hi>and write it, and our Princes, Levites, and Prieſts ſeale unto it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now here is the full accompliſhment of that you have in my Text. What in the Text is ſet downe by way of Propheſse you here ſee acted in the Hiſtory. In <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time, they come home unto it. And if you looke into the tenth Chapter, you ſhall ſee who ſealed this Covenant: firſt, the Princes, the Officers, the Magiſtrates of the Kingdome, the <hi>Parliament men,</hi> if you will ſo call them; and then the reſt of the people. And what is the ſubſtance of their Covenant? They <hi>entred into a curſe, and into an Oath, to walke in Gods Law, which was given by Moſes the ſervant of God, and to obſerve and doe all the Commandements of the Lord their God, and his Iudgements, and Statutes,</hi> verſe 29.</p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65562:10"/>
            <p>Here then is their Covenant:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> How it is ſo.</note> you ſee alſo with what ſolemnitie it was made and ratified; by <hi>ſubſcribing</hi> of <hi>hands,</hi> and ſetting to of their <hi>Seales,</hi> by an <hi>Oath,</hi> and by a <hi>curſe;</hi> binding themſelves by all the moſt ſolemne and ſtrongeſt bonds that poſſibly they could; and all this in Publique, and at a <hi>Publique Faſt,</hi> So that now the point is cleare, <hi>That it is ſo,</hi> and that the practiſe of Gods people hath ever beene, upon any great deliverance, eſpecially from <hi>Babylon,</hi> to enter into ſolemne Covenant with the Lord.</p>
            <p>Come we to the ſecond branch propounded, which is the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">2. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Quomodo ſit. How this is to be done</note> ſhewing, <hi>in what manner</hi> this Covenant muſt be made, and <hi>how</hi> men are to joyne themſelves to the Lord in this Action.</p>
            <p>This I ſhall demonſtrate out of the bowels of the Text it ſelfe: for therein may you ſee ſomewhat required, 1. By way of <hi>diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>preparation</hi> to it. 2. In reſpect of the <hi>ſubſtance</hi> of it. 3.<note place="margin">In a three fold reſpect</note> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the <hi>properties</hi> belonging to it. Theſe being opened, I ſhall give you a full view of this Text, and performe my promiſe before made unto you.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing to be unfolded is,<note place="margin">1 Of the diſpoſition requiſite to ſtrike a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God. Whereunto is required 1 the asking the way to Zion.</note> the <hi>diſpoſition</hi> or <hi>preparation</hi> to the <hi>Covenant;</hi> and this appeares in two things, 1 In ſeeking ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly the face of God, <hi>They ſhall aske the way to Zion.</hi> 2, In the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their addreſſe unto him, <hi>with their faces thitherward,</hi> ſaying, <hi>Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt thing requiſite to <hi>diſpoſe,</hi> qualifie, and prepare men to ſtrike a Covenant with God, is a ſerious and humble ſeeking of the face of God. <hi>They ſhall aske the way to Zjon.</hi> And there firſt a word of the place toward which they were bound; ſecondly, of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and repaire to it, under that expreſſion of <hi>asking the way</hi> thither.</p>
            <p>The <hi>place,</hi> was <hi>Zion,</hi> where firſt (though it be but a Criticiſme, it is yet not unneceſſary to be taken notice of, becauſe the word is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten pronounced, and written amiſſe, which may cauſe ambiguity touching the place) you muſt put a difference betweene <hi>Sihon</hi> or <hi>Sion,</hi> and <hi>Zion:</hi> (for theſe were two different places, and are written in the originall with two different Letters, the former with ש,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> the other with צ) you muſt not here underſtand this, of the former, namely, of <hi>Mount Sihon,</hi> which is all one with <hi>Hermon,</hi> ſituate in the utmoſt confines of Iſrael North-Eaſt-ward, neere unto Iordan, (<hi>Deut.</hi> 4.48.) but conceive it to be meant of <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Zion</hi> in Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65562:11"/> which was once the ſtrong hold of the Iebuſites,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> How this is to bee done.</note> and held out longer unſubdued than any Peece belonging to that people. For, when Iſrael under the Conduct of <hi>Ioſhua</hi> had conquered <hi>Iebus,</hi> after called <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> yet could they not winne <hi>Zion</hi> in it. <hi>Zion</hi> was a ſtrong Caſtle or Fort, erected upon a rocky mount, toward the South-weſt part of the City, overlooking all the reſt; and that the Iebuſites, having abundantly fortified and victualled it, ſtill held, all the daies of <hi>Ioſhuah,</hi> and long after, albeit the Iſraelites poſſeſſed the reſt of the City, <hi>Ioſh.</hi> 15.63. But afterwards when <hi>David came</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, even that <hi>ſtrong hold</hi> (which the Iebuſites thought to be ſo invincible, that, in ſcorne of him and his ſiege, they ſet up onely a few blinde and lame people on the walles to defend it) he conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and called it <hi>the City of David,</hi> becauſe after he had wonne it, himſelfe dwelt in it. 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 5.7. This, for the Topography.</p>
            <p>Then, you muſt know further, that, by <hi>Zion</hi> is ſometimes meant the whole city of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> by a <hi>Synechdoche;</hi> ſometimes it was taken for the place of Gods worſhip in the Holy city, or rather with reference to his Worſhip and preſence there: for that City being the Capitall City of the Kingdome, where Thrones were ſet for judgement, was alſo the ſpeciall place which God choſe to place his name in: there were the Altars placed for Gods worſhip, and <hi>thither the Tribes went up to worſhip,</hi> becauſe there God plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to manifeſt his more ſpeciall preſence, and to <hi>command the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for evermore.</hi> Thither therefore theſe returning Captives re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired; even unto <hi>Zion,</hi> the <hi>Watch Towre,</hi> as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prets it, whence God in ſpeciall manner watched over his people, for Good: there they ſeek his face, and enquire of him, before they preſume to enter Covenant with him.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> to beſeech or pray.</note>Now, their addreſſe to this place, is ſet forth in this Text, by <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the way</hi> to Zion. The word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> though it ſometimes import the demanding of a thing which is a point of juſtice or equity to give, (as Gen. 34.14.) yet is it uſually applyed to note the ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſome thing by humble prayers and intreaties: ſo as it is not ſeldome put for prayer it ſelfe, 2 <hi>Chro:</hi> 20.4. and, ſometimes for an earneſt and humble enquiry after ſome thing we know not, (<hi>Num:</hi> 27.21. <hi>Deut:</hi> 13.14.) that we may be directed aright, and purſue the direction with effect: ſo here, They <hi>aske the way to Zion,</hi> and that of God not onely <hi>to ſeek of him a right way for them</hi> by faſting
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65562:11"/> and prayer, <hi>Ezra</hi> 8.21. but, as reſolving that ſomewhat ſhould be done, that they would walke in it, and <hi>appeare before God in Zion:</hi> for, ſo much is intended here as is expreſſed more fully elſewhere, viz. in <hi>Iſay</hi> 2. <hi>verſe</hi> 2.3. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4.1, 2. where they not onely call on each other to undertake, but they alſo performe the journey, <hi>going up to the mountaine of the Lord.</hi> So the Prophet <hi>Zachary,</hi> the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of one <hi>City ſhall goe to another, ſaying, Let us goe ſpeedily to pray before the Lord, and to ſeeke the Lord of Hoſts, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Zac. 8.21.22.</note> And how goe they? not ſleightly, careleſſely, proudly, but in all humility, yea, (as in the verſe before my Text) even with <hi>weeping,</hi> they ſhall ſeek the Lord their God with deepe humiliation and godly ſorrow for all thoſe ſinnes whereby they had formerly broken his covenant, and for which he had entred upon the forfeiture, and laid thoſe heavy afflictions upon their Loines. <hi>Going, and weeping, they ſhall goe to ſeeke their God</hi> in <hi>Zion.</hi> The very ſame thing was foretold before (to ſhew the necesſity of the duty) touching Iſrael. <hi>Ier.</hi> 31.9. <hi>They ſhall come with weeping, &amp; with ſupplications will I lead them.</hi> So then, this is the firſt thing in this worke, to diſpoſe and prepare men for the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; namely, to <hi>aske the way</hi> to <hi>Zion,</hi> by a ſerious, humble, affectionate inquiring and ſeeking after God in his Ordinances, even with many prayers and teares, that he would be pleaſed to accept them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>manner</hi> of their addreſſe is as neceſſary as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. It is not every <hi>manner</hi> that will ſerve the turne. It muſt be done with all <hi>intention</hi> of ſpirit<note place="margin">2. In regard of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. That is, 1. With in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of Spirit.</note> in regard of themſelves, and with <hi>fervent Charity</hi> towards others. For, they muſt aske the way to Zion <hi>with their faces thitherward, ſaying Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Their <hi>intention and fervency of ſpirit</hi> wherewith they ſet upon this worke, is ſet forth under that Hebraiſme of asking the way to Zion <hi>with their faces thitherward.</hi> This phraſe is uſually an expreſſion of the greateſt intention, fervency, and contention of mind that can be, in the purſuit of any buſineſſe on foot, or of any way wherein a man is going. Such a phraſe you have in <hi>Luke</hi> 9.51. where it is ſaid of CHRIST, <hi>that he ſtedfaſtly ſet his face to goe to Ieruſalem,</hi> or, <hi>as if he would goe to Ieruſalem:</hi> for which cauſe the Samaritanes <hi>would not receive him,</hi> ver. 53. that is, they would not entertaine him with any reſpect, becauſe, that <hi>ſtedfast ſetting of his face</hi> towards Ieruſalem<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. He will no longer turne aſide hither, and thither and go about their villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. Tit. Boſt. in Luc. 9.</note> manifeſted, by his very countenance and aſpect, that, where ever his body was, his heart was at Ieruſalem (which the Samaritanes could
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65562:12"/> not brooke) and that nothing in the world could take him off from that journey, or, ſo farre prevaile with him, as to make him linger, or loyter upon the way; no entreaties, feare, ſhame, nor any thing could ſtay him, but <hi>obſtinata &amp; imperterrita mente locum petiit,</hi> as it is expreſt by <hi>Bede.</hi> He was no way afraid, or aſhamed to be ſeene and knowne whither he was bound, and what he was going about.</p>
            <p>When therefore it is here ſaid, they ſhall aske the way to Zion <hi>with their faces thitherward,</hi> the thing meant thereby, is, that they ſhall ſet upon this work with their whole heart, with their whole man, without any feare, or being aſhamed, or unwilling to owne the buſineſſe: but, they ſhall doe it thoroughly and affectionately without wavering, lingring, halting: they ſhall doe it boldly, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently, openly, indefatigably and continually. In a word, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver can be ſaid, or thought upon, to ſet forth the utmoſt intention of a mans Spirit in any worke, that his heart is moſt ſet upon, and that hee would lay out his life and all that he hath upon, for the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of it; that was the reſolution, and care of theſe people, and muſt be ours: this is to aske the way to Zion <hi>with our faces thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therward.</hi> And without this, no entring into Covenant with God. This is, for ſubſtance no other (though otherwiſe expreſſed) than that of the people in <hi>Aſa</hi> his time, when they ſware the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant before mentioned, 2 <hi>Chronicles verſe</hi> 15. where it is ſaid, they did it <hi>with all their heart, and with all their ſoule,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſt it by the <hi>loudneſſe</hi> of their <hi>voyces,</hi> and <hi>with ſhoutings,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>rejoycing at the Oath, becauſe they had ſworne with all their hearts, and ſought him with their whole deſire, verſ.</hi> 15. Men that will ſtand diſputing, conſulting with fleſh and bloud, and caſting about how the entring into ſuch a Covenant may conſiſt with their profits, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, luſts, deſignes, relations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are no fit <hi>Covenanters</hi> for <hi>God. His people ſhall be willing, Pſal.</hi> 110.3. their heart, mind, ſpirit, bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, countenance, all, ſhall profeſſe, and proclaime this to the whole world, that they are for God, for a <hi>Covenant,</hi> for putting themſelves into the ſtrongeſt bonds that can poſſibly bee thought on, to bind them hand and foot, ſoule and body to the Lord for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">2. With charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note>2. Nor is this all. For, the men in my Text, content not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be thus earneſtly addicted to the worke in their owne par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars; but, (as one ſticke kindles another) they deſire to kindle the ſame flame of affection in others alſo, and mutually to blow
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65562:12"/> up the Coales in one another, <hi>ſaying, Come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This notes the <hi>fervency</hi> of their <hi>Charitie</hi> towards others alſo. For, 'tis not here brought in as a formality, or complement, but as the evidence of a ſtrong deſire to draw as many others as they can to the ſame journey, and (if it be poſſible) to keepe the ſame pace with them, as being moſt unwilling to leave any behind them. This indeed is true Love, unfained Charitie, to draw all we can along with us unto God. True Converts, when once they returne them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>They cauſe others to returne</hi> alſo. And this was often prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied as a thing which ſhould certainely bee: Witneſſe all thoſe pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in <hi>Iſay</hi> 2. <hi>Mic.</hi> 4. and <hi>Zach.</hi> 8. before quoted. So then all theſe things are requiſite, and <hi>previous</hi> to the Act of Covenanting with God. There muſt bee a ſeeking to God with true Humiliation, a ſeeking of him with all intention of ſpirit, and with all manifeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of a reſolution not to be terrified from, daunted at, or aſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the worke: yea, with fervent Charity to draw others into the ſame Covenant alſo. Thus much for the diſpoſition previous to the Covenant.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing conſiderable in the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is, the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of the Covenant<note place="margin">2. The Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. Both in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect,</note> it ſelfe. <hi>Let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord, in a Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Two things here muſt be opened; the <hi>matter,</hi> and the <hi>forme</hi> of this ſolemne action.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The matter<note place="margin">1. Of the matter.</note> of this Act is ſet forth under this expreſſion, <hi>Let us joyne our ſelves to the Lord.</hi> The originall word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (from <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) is very emphaticall; ſo as that word, being explained, will ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſet out before you the nature of the Covenant here inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Some Tranſlators render it, <hi>Let us glue our ſelves unto the Lord;</hi> which imports a conjunction ſo neere, as nothing can come betweene, and ſo firme, as nothing can diſſolve. But more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly, the verb here uſed is in Scripture applyed to a double ſenſe, or to denote two things: both of which being ſet together, will fully diſcover what it is to be <hi>joyned to the Lord in Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, it ſignifieth the binding of a mans ſelfe t the Vſurer, of whom he hath borrowed money, to pay backe both principall and intereſt. So it is uſed in <hi>Nehem.</hi> 5.4. where the people complaine, <hi>Wee have borrowed money</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>, <hi>for the Kings tribute, and that upon our Lands and Vineyards.</hi> That is, they had engaged both Lands and Vineyards for ſecuritie of the money borrowed, that the Vſurer
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65562:13"/> ſhould enter upon all, in caſe they failed of payment at the day. So that, as men, to make ſure, will have a <hi>Statute Staple,</hi> or <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogniſance in the nature of a Statute Staple,</hi> acknowledged, whereby a mans perſon, goods, lands, and all, are bound for the ſecuritie of the Creditor, that he ſhall have both principall and intereſt at the day agreed upon (and here that of <hi>Solomon</hi> proves too true, <hi>The borrower is ſervant to the lender:</hi> for, he hath nothing left to his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; if he would ſell any land, ſettle any joyncture, there is a <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute</hi> upon it, he can diſpoſe of nothing till that be taken off;) ſo it is in the caſe of any man joyning himſelfe to the Lord by Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, he muſt even bind himſelfe to God as firmely, as fully, as the poore borrower, who for his neceſſitie takes up money, binds him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to the Vſurer. If God lend him any mercy, any bleſſing, he binds himſelfe to reſtore not only the principall (the bleſſing it ſelfe) when God ſhall call for it; but even the intereſt too; I meane, all poſſible homage, ſervice, and honour which becomes thoſe who have received ſo great a benefit.</p>
            <p>This is more than implyed in that parable of our Saviour touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the talents diſpenſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.27. for even to him who had received but one talent, was it ſaid, <hi>Thou oughteſt to have put my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the Exchangers, that at my comming I might have received mine owne with uſury.</hi> God will have his returne, ſome intereſt, for every mercy; and expects a <hi>Statute Staple,</hi> that is, a Covenant, for his bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſecurity. God will have him bound, ſoule, body, eſtate, life and all; ſo as all he is, and hath, ſhall be forfeited, if he do not keep touch, and make payment according to the agreement and Covenant made betweene them. This is the firſt uſe of the word, <hi>Nilvu.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, there is yet more in it. For, though it be true that the obligation of a borrower to the uſurer be as ſtrong as bonds and Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes can make it; yet, there is not ſuch an entire, neere, firme, and laſting tye of the borrower to the Lender, nor ſuch a thorough inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the whole eſtate of the Vſurer, as there is of him that is in Covenant with God. The Vſurer, though he bind the poore bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower faſt to him, yet he keepes him at diſtance, not giving him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in, or uſe of any other part of his eſtate, but onely of the ſum borrowed. But now this <hi>joyning of our ſelves to the Lord,</hi> is ſuch, as is made by <hi>marriage;</hi> &amp; gives intereſt in all that the Lord is, and hath, and admits us to the participation of all the moſt intimate, neereſt,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65562:13"/> choyſeſt expreſſions of the deereſt Love of God, which is or can be found betweene the husband and the wife, who are <hi>joyned</hi> together by the bond of marriage, and made one fleſh.</p>
            <p>So the word is uſed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 29.34. where <hi>Leah,</hi> being delivered of her third ſon, <hi>Levi,</hi> thus ſaith to the women about her, <hi>Now this time will my husband be joyned</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>unto me, becauſe I have borne him three ſons.</hi> That is, now ſhall my husband be more arctly united to me in all love, and in all demonſtrations of it, and that in the moſt free, full, and intimate way of expreſſion that poſſibly can paſſe between thoſe who are coupled together in ſo neere a relation.</p>
            <p>So then, lay both theſe together, and you have a cleare view of this <hi>joyning of our ſelves to the Lord</hi> by Covenant. He that enters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Covenant with God, doth not only bind himſelfe, as the needy <hi>borrower</hi> to the Covetous Vſurer, for a <hi>time;</hi> but, as the <hi>Wife</hi> to the <hi>Husband,</hi> to be <hi>wholly his for ever,</hi> without any reſervation, limita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or termination, till death diſſolve the bond. As the wife hath intereſt in the goods, eſtate, and perſon of the husband; and all that he hath is hers: ſo by this <hi>joyning of our ſelves to the Lord,</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes ours, as well as we become his, and both are mutually con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to each other by an indiſſoluble bond for ever. All the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, wiſdome, goodneſſe, mercy, grace, glory, that the Great God hath to communicate to the creature, is now aſſured and made over to every ſoule that thus engageth himſelfe unto him. And on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide, all the wit, ſtrength, induſtry, wealth, honour, friends, life, and all that this man hath, he makes over, and reſignes up actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, totally, abſolutely, and for ever unto the Lord, to ſerve and honour him withall; and that with all his heart, and with his whole deſire; to have nothing, to doe nothing, to be nothing but for the Lord, though all the world be againſt him for it. This I take to be the full latitude of the <hi>Covenant,</hi> for the <hi>Matter</hi> of it.</p>
            <p n="2">2.<note place="margin">2. In regard of the forme</note> Touching the <hi>forme</hi> of this Act of <hi>joyning our ſelves to the Lord,</hi> it is expreſſed in the word <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Covenant.</hi> A Covenant is nothing elſe but an agreement or bargaine betweene two or moe perſons, and ratified (ordinarily) by ſome externall ſolemnity, or rites that may teſtifie and declare the agreement, whereby it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes unalterable. Therefore it is, that among the variety of rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of Covenants mentioned in Scripture, ſtill there is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of outward ſolemnity reported to have beene uſed at the mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65562:14"/> of them, to ſtrike the bargaine thorough.</p>
            <p>Sometimes they were made by <hi>Sacrifice, Pſalme</hi> 50.5. ſometimes by <hi>Oath, Deut.</hi> 29. ſometimes by an <hi>Oath,</hi> and a <hi>curſe, Neh.</hi> 10.29. ſometimes by <hi>ſubſcription</hi> of their hands,<note place="margin">Iſa. 44.5. Neh. 9. ult.</note> ſometimes by <hi>ſealing</hi> it with their ſeales alſo: Sometimes by all theſe, and by what ever elſe might moſt firmely and inviolably knit men unto God. And as it was then, ſo muſt it be ſtill. To ſtrike a Covenant, is not, in a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate or publike prayer only, to goe to God and ſay, <hi>Lord I will bee thine, I here enter into a Covenant with thee, be thou a witneſſe of it, &amp;c.</hi> but it is, to ſtand and make it <hi>publiquely</hi> before the Lord, by ſome ſpeciall <hi>ſolemnity</hi> that may <hi>witnes</hi> it to all the world, as <hi>Ioſiah</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 34.31.</note>, <hi>Aſa,</hi> and all the godly ever did; (even as in entring into bonds, or as in ſolemnizing of matrimony, men uſe to doe.) Whether by the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> by <hi>fasting,</hi> or by ought elſe, whereby they may becom ſo firmely and arctly joyned to the Lord, that they may not only be no longer <hi>ſui juris,</hi> to depart away from the living God; but, not ſo much as to ſit looſe from God, or to ſtand in any termes of indifferency, which might leave them at liberty to ſerve, or not to ſerve God in any dutie how difficult, or dangerous ſoever. And thus have you the Subſtance of the Covenant opened.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Take we now a ſhort view of the <hi>properties</hi> of this Covenant, and they are two;<note place="margin">3. The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, which are two.</note> 
               <hi>perpetuitie</hi> and <hi>heedfulneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. It muſt be an <hi>everlaſting Covenant,</hi> in regard of continuance.<note place="margin">1. It muſt be everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance.</note> In the Originall it is <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>a Covenant of Ages.</hi> And the 72. <hi>Interpreters</hi> render it to the ſame purpoſe, <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, ſuch a Covenant as no time ſhall terminate, till they who make it ceaſe to be. Some underſtand this of engaging themſelves to ſticke cloſe to him in the due celebration of his Legall worſhip, ſo long as hee ſhould continue it in his Church, (which was, till <hi>Shiloh</hi> came) without thoſe mixtures, wherein formerly they had been too bold, and for which God had ſpewed them out of his Church, and hurled them as farre as Babylon. Others conceive it to be meant of the <hi>Covenant of Grace</hi> that God had ſealed to them in the bloud of his Sonne. But, neither of theſe are full. For, it is clearely meant of an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>theirs</hi> towards <hi>God,</hi> whereby they bind themſelves to him, and that not for a definite time only, but for ever.</p>
            <p>It is ſuch a binding, as that of the borrower to the Vſur r, whom nothing can ſatisfie but full payment. Or rather, ſuch a cloſing with
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65562:14"/> God, as is that of the wife to the husband, called, in particular re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference to the nuptiall knot, <hi>the Covenant of her God, Prov.</hi> 2.17. She muſt be his for ever; that is, <hi>ſo long as ſhe liveth, Rom.</hi> 7. So that, for men to bind themſelves by an everlaſting <hi>Covenant</hi> to the Lord, is to bind themſelves never to ſtep out from him to Idols, to their baſe luſts, to any creature, in any ſtrait, upon any occaſion, or ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation whatſoever; nor, with the dogge, to returne any more to their vomit of any kind. They are in Covenant as the wife to the husband; for they are <hi>marryed unto the Lord for ever, Hoſ.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p n="2">2. It muſt be <hi>heeded</hi> and <hi>minded;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 It muſt be heeded, and not forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten.</note> elſe, it will be to ſmall purpoſe to be ſo <hi>laſting.</hi> It muſt be a Covenant <hi>that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Covenant, <hi>quod non tradetur oblivioni;</hi> as <hi>Tremellius</hi> well: that is, that ſhall not be <hi>cast behind their backs.</hi> It is but a plaine mocke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for men ſo to enter Covenant with God, as young Gallants en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into bonds to the Vſurer, never thinking more of them, till the day of payment be paſt, and the Sergeant ready to attach them. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the wicked ſaith God, what haſt thou to doe to take my Covenant into thy mouth, ſeeing thou caſteſt my words behind thee?</hi> Pſalme 50. Only they rightly performe this dutie, who ſo joyne themſelves to the Lord, as to <hi>remember,</hi> and <hi>minde</hi> the obligation they have ſealed. As a poore man that meanes honeſtly, if he be neceſſitated to take up mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney upon his bond, he can hardly eate, walke, ſleep, doe any thing, be in any company, but that ſtill his minde runs upon the obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and day of payment: he complaines he is in debt, he hath given bond for ſo much money, and all his care is how to pay his debts, or to get longer time; ſo it is with a Godly man that hath entred Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with the Lord, he hath ſealed a bond, and he knowes it muſt be ſatisfied, or it will be put in ſuit. Therefore he <hi>beares it in minde,</hi> he is alwayes caſting about how he may performe, and keep touch with God. <hi>I will never forget thy precepts,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, I have incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mine heart to performe thy Statutes alwayes, even unto the end,</hi> Pſal. 119.112. This is one expreſſion.</p>
            <p>Againe, It is a Covenant to be <hi>remembred,</hi> as that of the <hi>wife,</hi> whereby ſhe ſtands bound to her <hi>husband:</hi> ſhe muſt ever remember it. It is the note of an Harlot to <hi>forget the Covenant of her</hi> GOD. The chaſte wife will ſo <hi>remember</hi> the marriage bond,<note place="margin">Pro. 2.17.</note> that if ſhe be ſolicited to unfaithfulneſſe, to uncleanneſſe, &amp;c. ſhe ever hath this in her thoughts, that ſhe hath given her ſelfe wholly away to an hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65562:15"/> and is bound to keep her only unto him during life; and this makes her to be even an impregnable wall againſt all aſſaults that might otherwiſe draw her to folly. So muſt it be in the caſe in hand: The Covenant muſt ſtill be in the <hi>heart,</hi> and in the <hi>memory.</hi> In every action of a mans life, in every paſſage and turning of his eſtate and condition, in every deſigne or engagement, <hi>this</hi> muſt <hi>not be forgotten;</hi> viz. <q rend="inline">I have entred into Covenant with God, as a wife with her husband; will that I am now doing, or going about, ſtand with my Covenant?</q> Is this to performe Covenant with God? &amp;c. If he be ſolicited to uncleanneſſe, to fraud, oppreſſion, any evill what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, this ſtill runs in his minde, There is a Covenant between me and the Lord, I am bound from ſuch courſes by the ſtrongeſt bonds; <hi>How then can I commit this great wickedneſſe, and ſinne againſt God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 78.10.</note>What was it for which <hi>Judah,</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> became <hi>Captives,</hi> but the breach of the Covenant? <hi>They kept not the Covenant of God,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt. And, how ſo? becauſe they did <hi>not remember</hi> it. As <hi>they ſoone forgot his workes,</hi> ſo it was not long ere they <hi>forgot God their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> himſelfe too; and then no marvaile, if, at the next bout, they forgot his <hi>Covenant</hi> alſo, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106, He then, that would not <hi>breake</hi> Covenant, muſt <hi>not forget</hi> it; but <hi>mind,</hi> and performe it. Otherwiſe, it is like <hi>vowing unto God, and not paying,</hi> which is worſe than <hi>not to vow</hi> at all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.</note>Thus have I diſpatcht the Second <hi>generall,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and ſhewed you <hi>how</hi> and <hi>in what manner</hi> this Covenant muſt be ſtriken: <hi>firſt,</hi> in regard of the <hi>diſpoſition and preparation</hi> of the Soule unto it, it muſt be with <hi>ſerious ſeeking</hi> the face of God and humbling the ſoule before hand; it muſt be with al <hi>intention</hi> &amp; <hi>earneſtnes,</hi> with fervent <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> to draw others the ſame way. <hi>Next,</hi> in regard of the <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> it ſelfe, it muſt be an <hi>act and firm joyning</hi> and <hi>binding</hi> our ſelves to the Lord, as of the <hi>borrower</hi> to the <hi>Lender;</hi> of the <hi>wife</hi> to the <hi>husband;</hi> and that by ſome <hi>ſolemne Act,</hi> which may <hi>teſtifie</hi> it to all the world, and be a <hi>witneſſe</hi> againſt us, if we keep it not. And all this, thirdly for <hi>properties,</hi> muſt be of <hi>everlasting continuance,</hi> and had in <hi>continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance,</hi> ſo as it may be continually performed of all that make it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <note place="margin">3. <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur fit. the grounds why it is ſo: theſe are of 2 ſorts viz.</note>3. I proceed to the third and laſt branch, the <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>reaſons why,</hi> upon receit of <hi>any deliverance,</hi> but more eſpecially from <hi>Babylon,</hi> people ſhould enter into ſuch a covenant with God. And theſe reſpect deliverances either in <hi>general,</hi> or from <hi>Babylon</hi> in <hi>ſpecial.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65562:15"/>
            <p n="1">1. The reaſons why this muſt be done, upon <hi>any deliverance</hi> in generall,<note place="margin">1. Why, for any delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall.</note> are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe God, at no time ſo much as when he beſtowes upon his people ſome notable deliverance,<note place="margin">1 God at ſuch times gives clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of his readineſſe to enter co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with us.</note> gives ſuch cleere hints and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of his willingneſſe to ſtrike an everlaſting Covenant with them. No ſooner had the Lord delivered Iſrael out of Egypt, but within 3. Moneths after, he commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to tell the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from him; <hi>Ye have ſeene what I did unto the Egyptians; and how I bare you on Eagles wings, and brought you out unto my ſelfe. Now there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if ye will obey my voyce and keep my Covenant, then yee ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me above all people.</hi> Exod. 19.1. and <hi>verſe</hi> 4.5. God himſelfe, you ſee, was now earneſt for a <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is the nature of God, where he beſtowes one benefit, to adde moe, and ſtill to riſe in his bleſſings. Where he once opens his hand to take a people into his protection, he opens his heart to take them into his <hi>boſome.</hi> Where he puts forth his <hi>power</hi> to <hi>reſcue</hi> a people, he puts out his heart to make them <hi>his owne,</hi> if then they have eyes to diſcerne the opportunity. See this moſt excellently demonſtrated <hi>Ier.</hi> 32. from <hi>ver.</hi> 37. to the 42. His gathering them from their <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity,</hi> firſt warmes, then melts, and after inflames his heart towards them, making it even then to glow as it were upon them, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come reſtleſſe till he have beſtowed himſelfe wholly on them by ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne <hi>Covenant</hi> to be their God for ever.</p>
            <p>Now then, ſhall God, at ſuch a time, be ſo willing and deſirous to enter Covenant with men, and ſhall they think it too much for them to be in Covenant with him? Shall he be faſt bound to them, and they left free to ſit looſe from him? Indeed, this is that which our corrupt nature would willingly have: People would faine be their owne men; which yet in truth, is, to be the greateſt ſlaves. Neceſſary therefore it is for men, upon receit of <hi>any deliverance,</hi> to renew Covenant with God who is pleaſed to honour them ſo farre, as to be in Covenant with them. For, theſe two are relatives, and ever goe together, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi> God is not the God of any people but of his owne Covenant-Servants. The reſt, he ſtiles, <hi>Lo-ammi.</hi> Hoſ. 1.9. <hi>for yee are not my people,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and I wil not be your God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. God is content to be bound, firſt.</note> They will not enter into Covenant with me, and I wil make no Covenant with them. That is the firſt reaſon.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As God is pleaſed to enter into Covenant with his people, ſo
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:65562:16"/> is he <hi>firſt</hi> in the Covenant,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Why it is ſo,</hi> in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall.</note> God requires no man to bind himſelfe by Covenant to Him, till the Lord firſt ſtrike a Covenant with his Soule. As <hi>wee love him, becauſe hee loved us firſt;</hi> ſo we enter into Covenant with him, becauſe he firſt entreth into Covenant with us. I <hi>will be their God,</hi> he is firſt bound, and ſeales firſt; and then, and not till then, it followes; <hi>they ſhall be my people.</hi> This is the conſtant tenor of the Covenant. And ſhall he begin, and we thinke much to follow? Can there be a marriage conſummated where only the man is firſt married to the woman, and the woman will not after, for her part, be married to the man? Now, God no way ſo much declares his willingneſſe to be in Covenant, and to be <hi>firſt</hi> in it, as by delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances (as we ſhall ſee more in the next reaſon:) great reaſon there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, men ſhould then ſecond him by mutuall ſtipulation. It is an hard caſe, when men will not fellow, where God leades.</p>
            <p n="3">3. In deliverances God more eſpecially manifeſteth his fidelity in <hi>keeping Covenant</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. In delie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances God more eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſteth his fidelity in the Grand Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant. Pſal. 107.</note> with his people, even when they have <hi>broken Covenant</hi> with him, and forfeited all into his hands. When God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers a people out of any ſtraite, doth not that uſually ſuppoſe ſome <hi>folly</hi> of theirs going before, and provoking him to caſt them into that affliction; whence, upon their <hi>cry,</hi> he is pleaſed to deliver them.</p>
            <p>And when they have ſo farre and ſo long broken the Lawes, and contemned the counſell of the moſt high, and <hi>dealt unfaithfully in his Covenant,</hi> as that he hath beene even compelled to throw them into <hi>darkneſſe and the ſhadow of death:</hi> yet if then, upon their humiliation, he be pleaſed to <hi>deliver them out of all their diſtreſſes;</hi> this is to give them freſh experience of his infinite love in <hi>Keeping Covenant and mercy</hi> with them, that kept no Covenant with him. This is called <hi>a remembring of his Covenant</hi> with his people, after that <hi>their uncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed hearts be humbled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Levit. 26.41, 42.</note> 
               <hi>and that they accept of the puniſhment of their iniquity,</hi> when God ſhould have caſt them out of their land, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong their enemies, as afterwards he did. So that, in a deliverance, that which is moſt predominant in God, and ſhould be moſt ſweet and pretious to his people and moſt eyed by them, is his fidelity, mercy, and unchangeable Love in bringing out that Covenant he once made with them, and ſpreading it before himſelfe, and making of it good, even when they could not expect it, nor durſt to plead it. Hence that paſſionate ſpeech of God to rebellious <hi>Ephraim. Is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraim my deare ſonne?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>c. 31.20</note> 
               <hi>is he a pleaſant child?</hi> As if he ſhould have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65562:16"/> ſaid, ſurely he cannot conclude ſo; yet, my love, by vertue of the ancient Covenant betweene us, makes me ſtill ſo to account him: witneſſe that which followes; <hi>for ſince I ſpake againſt him,</hi> (that is, as reſolving to caſt him off for ever) <hi>I remember him ſtill,</hi> (I remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber I am in Covenant with him,) <hi>therefore my bowels are troubled for him, I will ſurely have mercy upon him, ſaith the Lord:</hi> Thus, deliverance is a thread drawne out of the bowells of his Covenant. Great reaſon therefore that, in this caſe, his people ſhould thinke of renewing their league and Covenant with the Lord on their parts, when they have ſo ſhamefully broken it, and yet he goes on in ſo much mercy to manifeſt his fidelity in <hi>remembring</hi> and <hi>keeping</hi> the Covenant on his part, by giving them deliverance.</p>
            <p>Againe, fourthly and laſtly, All our hopes of a <hi>full deliverance,</hi> of compleat happineſſe, will be delayed, if not fruſtrate; and,<note place="margin">4 No complete deliverance and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> the next deliverance wil ſtick in the birth, and want ſtrength to bring forth, if we come not up to a Covenant for deliverances already received. If God have delivered us once, he will doe it no more: or if he doe ſomewhat, to hold us up by the chin that we ſink not, yet will he hold us downe from the throne, that we reigne not, till we come up actually and fully in this point of Covenanting with him. It is only to thoſe that <hi>take hold of his Covenant,</hi> that he <hi>gives an everlaſting name which ſhall not be cut off,</hi> Iſa. 56.4, 5.</p>
            <p>He that hath obtained moſt and greateſt deliverances, will ere long, ſtand in need of more. Now, one thing is neceſſary to draw downe more, and to move God to <hi>command (further) deliverances for Iacob;</hi> yea, to powre out his whole boſome into the laps of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and to crowne all deliverances and bleſſings received, with this aſſurance, that he that <hi>hath delivered,</hi> will yet <hi>againe deliver;</hi> and that <hi>is,</hi> to enter into a ſolemne Covenant with the Lord, upon conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of what he hath done already, how ever he ſhould pleaſe to deale with us for the future, or for removing any preſent preſſures that lye upon us. Although God begin to deliver,<note place="margin">See Iudg. 10 from verſ. 9 to verſe 17</note> yet he will never perfect the deliverance, till this be done. The people which retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from <hi>Babylon,</hi> found God to keepe touch with them, to a day. So ſoone as the 70. yeares determined, their captivity was diſſolved, and ſomewhat was done, the <hi>foundation</hi> of the <hi>Lords houſe</hi> was laid, but the building went ſlowly up, the reformation of Church and State went heavily on; and, they were never in a thriving condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65562:17"/> till <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Why it is ſo</note> by the good hand of God, lighted upon this courſe. Some <hi>Faſts</hi> they had kept before, yea very many; but they never thrived, till he added to their publique and ſolemne <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,</hi> the faſtening of them to God by a <hi>ſolemne Covenant.</hi> Then, the worke of Reformation, and eſtabliſhment, went on merrily, then they proſpered. Thus farre the Reaſons concluding for a Covenant, upon receit of deliverances in <hi>generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The Reaſons inducing us thereunto, upon deliverance from <hi>Babylon</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 why, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance from Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, <hi>in ſpeciall.</hi>
               </note> in <hi>particular,</hi> are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe <hi>Babylon</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Babylon hath ever bin the ſoreſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</note> (after once the Church was put under her power) had alwaies been the moſt inſolent, heavy, bitter, bloody enemy that ever the Church felt. The violence of <hi>Babylon</hi> was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſupportable, her inſolency intolerable, her bloud-thirſtineſſe inſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able. Hence the Church is bold to challenge all the world to match her miſery under the yoke of Babylon; <hi>Behold, and ſee, if there be any ſorrow like unto my ſorrow, wherewith the Lord hath afflicted me,</hi> (that is, by the heavie hand of Babylon) <hi>in the day of his fierce wrath, Lam.</hi> 1.12.</p>
            <p>This was ſo ſore, that it hath been by ſome Fathers, and others, conceived to be the fulleſt and moſt lively typical expreſſion of that matchleſſe agony and extremity which our Lord himſelfe (hanging upon the <hi>Croſſe</hi>) ſuſtained, when he bare all our ſins, and the wrath of God due to us for them, ſo farre as to make a full ſatisfaction to the Iuſtice of his Father, in behalfe of all his people.</p>
            <p>And, as it was with old <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſo it is now, and ever wil be with the new, (I meane, <hi>myſticall Babylon</hi>) to the end of the world; might ſhe ſo long continue. Even ſhe alſo delights in no other drink but the bloud of the Saints, as you ſhall finde in <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.5. where the very name written upon her forehead ſufficiently ſets out her na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Myſtery, Babylon the Great, the Mother of harlots and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the earth.</hi> And, what of her? <hi>I ſaw,</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn, the woman drunken with the bloud of the Saints, and with the bloud of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs of Ieſus: and when I ſaw her, I wondred with great admiration, v.</hi> 6. And well he might. A <hi>woman,</hi> and <hi>drunke!</hi> And, if <hi>drunke,</hi> would no liquor ſuffice, but <hi>bloud!</hi> no <hi>bloud,</hi> but that of <hi>Saints and Martyrs!</hi> She is never in her element, but when ſhe is ſwimming in bloud So inſatiable is ſhe, that like the <hi>horſe-leeches</hi> daughter, <hi>ſhe never ſaith, it is enough.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:65562:17"/>
            <p>Therefore, when God gives any deliverance from thence,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Why it is ſo, <hi>in ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall.</hi>
               </note> there is more than ordinary cauſe to cloſe with the Lord, in a more ſolemn and extraordinary manner, giving him the praiſe and glory of ſo great a mercy. But then more eſpecially, when God works out the <hi>full deliverance</hi> of his Church, by the totall and finall ruine of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.</hi> Oh then, then is the time when all the people in heaven muſt ſing <hi>Halleluiah;</hi> aſcribing, <hi>ſalvation, and honour, and power unto the Lord our God,</hi> Revel. 19.1. <hi>And againe, Halleluiah,</hi> verſe 3. as if they could never ſufficiently expreſſe themſelves to God for ſuch a deliverance, ſuch a mercy, ſuch a vengeance.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Againe. When God delivereth from <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Such a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes more than ordinary breach of Covenant on our parts, for which God formerly put us under ſuch a yoke.</note> there is more than ordinary cauſe of entring into ſolemne Covenant with him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the very ſubjecting of the Godly under that iron yoke, argues more than ordinary breach of Covenant with the Lord in time paſt, which ſtirred him up to deale ſo ſharply with them as to put them under the power of <hi>Babylon.</hi> This Provocation was exceeding great, too much to be endured even by infinite Patience it ſelfe: elſe, the People of God had never been caſt into ſuch a furnace. It was for ſuch a fault as diſſolved the very marriage knot between God and his people: it was for <hi>going a whoring from him.</hi> For this it was, that God firſt <hi>put away Iſrael,</hi> giving her a Bill of divorce, <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.8. And for this it was, that hee afterwards caſt <hi>Iudah</hi> alſo out of his ſight, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.19.29. And as it was in former times, ſo in later Ages of the world. What was the reaſon that ſo many millions of ſoules have been expoſed to the butchery of Antichriſt in Myſticall <hi>Babylon,</hi> and to bee ſo hood-winckt and blinded <hi>by ſtrong deluſions,</hi> as <hi>to beleeve</hi> nothing but lyes; even that Great, Great ſoul-killing <hi>Lye,</hi> that they might be damned? S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us, it was this; <hi>They received not the love of the truth that they might be ſaved,</hi> but <hi>had pleaſure in unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. What <hi>unrighteouſneſſe?</hi> Is it meant of every unrighteouſneſſe (that is in the nature of it damnable) which is to be found in the world? Surely no: but <hi>(ſignanter)</hi> of that <hi>unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> whereby men <hi>turned the truth of God into a lye.</hi> Rom. 1. that is, by corrupting the true worſhip of the true God, and afterwards fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling off to down-right Idolatry, even within the pales of the Church it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>Moſt of you are well ſeene in the Hiſtory of the Church, and can ſoone point with your finger to the times wherein <hi>Babylon</hi> began to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:65562:18"/> beſiege <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and <hi>Antichriſt</hi> began to pull off his vizzard, in the Churches of Chriſt: even then, when <hi>Pictures</hi> and <hi>Images</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan firſt to be ſet up in <hi>Churches,</hi> for <hi>remembrance:</hi> then, for <hi>orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment;</hi> then, for <hi>inſtruction</hi> too; and at laſt, for <hi>adoration</hi> and worſhip. Then, God ſuffered her to bee over-run, and over-ſpread by <hi>Babylon,</hi> as by an hideous <hi>opacum,</hi> or thick darkneſſe, and to bee expoſed and proſtituted to all manner of whoredomes and filthineſſe: ſo as the ſlavery of the Iewiſh Church in old <hi>Babylon,</hi> was ſcarce a flea-biting, in compariſon of the miſeries of the Church Chriſtian under the <hi>new,</hi> which makes havock and merchandiſe not of the bodies onely, but even <hi>of the ſoules of men,</hi> Revel. 18.13.</p>
            <p>Now then, when God pleaſeth to deliver a people from ſuch bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, and to awaken them effectually to look up, and to reflect even with aſtoniſhment upon thoſe great and gaſtly ſins of theirs, which had cut aſunder the cords of the Covenant betweene God and their Soules, and provoked God to ſubject them to ſo much bondage; and, that they muſt either renew Covenant, or bee obnoxious to more wrath, and be laid open to more and greater temptations and ſinnes; this cannot but exceedingly work upon their ſoules, cauſing their hearts to melt, and their very bowels to yearne after the Lord, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a new, <hi>an everlaſting Covenant that ſhall never be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is that which God by his ſervant <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſpake touching the deportment of the remnant of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which ſhould eſcape the ſword among the nations and countries whither they had been carried cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 6.9. They ſhould, upon ſuch a deliverance, <hi>remember</hi> God, not onely with griefe, but reſolution alſo to joyne themſelves to him more firmely in a perpetuall Covenant. For, of them, he ſaith there; <hi>they that eſcape of you ſhall remember mee among the nations, becauſe I am broken with their whoriſh heart which hath departed from me, and with their eyes which goe a whoring after their idols, and they ſhall loth themſelves for the evils which they have committed in all their abominations.</hi> And of the ſame people hee ſaith afterwards,<note n="*" place="margin">Cap. 11.18, 19, 20.</note> that, upon their returne home, <hi>They ſhall take away all the deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things, and all the abominations thereof from thence. And I will give them one heart, and put a new ſpirit within them, I will take away the ſtony heart out of their fleſh, and give them an heart of fleſh, that they may walke in my ſtatutes, and keepe mine ordinances, and doe them: and they ſhall bee my people, and I will bee their God.</hi> So that here is a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65562:18"/> full Covenant ſtriken, and that upon this ground: <hi>viz.</hi> the Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe great ſins they formerly committed, whereby they had broken their firſt Covenant and departed from their God.</p>
            <p>So farre the Reaſons, and Grounds of the point; I ſhall now as briefly as I can, endeavour to bring home, and ſet on all by ſome Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Application</hi> Threefold.</note> which I ſhall reduce to 3. heads, namely to matter of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe, Information</hi> and <hi>Exhortation.</hi> For, if <hi>When God vouchſafeth any deliverance to his people, eſpecially from Babylon, it bee moſt ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and neceſſary to cloſe with him, by a more ſolemne, firme, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violable Covenant, to be onely his for ever:</hi> Then,</p>
            <p n="1">1. How may this reprove,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Vſe,</hi> of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe.</hi>
               </note> and condemne of great ingratitude and folly, many ſorts of men among us, that are farre from making any ſuch uſe of the deliverances which God hath wrought for them? O beloved! Should I but give you a Catalogue of the many, great, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious, and even miraculous deliverances which God hath given us; the perſonall deliverances hee hath often given to each of us a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part; the publique, eminent, glorious deliverances hee hath given to us together with the whole State; that in 88. and that of 1605. I meane from the horrid helliſh <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon;</hi> but eſpecially, and above all the reſt, our happy deliverance out of <hi>Babylon</hi> by the bleſſed Reformation of Religion begun amongſt us, ſome good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of yeares by paſt; the time would faile me. But alas!<note place="margin">Of foure ſorts of men. viz. 1. Of ſuch as think a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, but not after delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.15.</note> What <hi>uſe</hi> have we made of them? Hath this <hi>uſe</hi> ever been ſo much as thought of by us? Nay verily. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Some think it bootleſſe, thus to <hi>cloſe</hi> in with God, after an evill is over. When Gods hand is heavy upon them, ſenſe of ſmart compels them to think it then a fit ſeaſon to doe ſomewhat, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their ſins, to humble themſelves, and to ſeek God. <hi>In their aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction they will ſeeke me early,</hi> ſaith the Lord. But ſo ſoone as hee takes his hand off from them, they caſt all care away, as if now (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that homely proverb) <hi>the devill were dead,</hi> and no further uſe of any feare, or diligence, were to be once thought upon, till (with <hi>Pharaoh</hi>) they come under a worſe plague than before; and, as if God had delivered them to no other end, but to live as they liſt, to caſt more dung into his face, and to diſhonour and provoke him yet more than ever before.</p>
            <p>I appeale to the conſciences of many who heare mee this day, and I require them from the Lord to witneſſe truly, whether it bee
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65562:19"/> not even thus with them.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Vſe. Reproofe.</note> If the plague knock at their doore, if death get in at the window, and begin to ſhake them by the hand; there is then ſome apprehenſion of wrath and judgement, ſome humbling, ſome hankering after Cod. Then, Oh what would not theſe men do, what would they not promiſe, on condition to bee delivered from their preſent anguiſh, and feares! But once deliver them, and God ſhall heare no more of them, till they bee in the ſame, or worſe caſe again. They turne <hi>Covenanters?</hi> Nay, leave that to the <hi>Puritans.</hi> For their parts, they think more of a <hi>Covenant with death and hell,</hi> for <hi>God is not in all their thoughts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Had there been, upon the diſcovery of the Powder-Treaſon (which this Honourable Aſſembly hath cauſe above all others to preſerve eternally in freſh remembrance, and to think more ſeriouſly what God looks for at all your hands upon ſuch a deliverance) had there been, I ſay, no poſſibility of eſcaping that Blow, what would not men have then done! Oh what prayers, what faſting, what humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation ſhould we have ſeene! But, when the ſnare was once broken, what followed? A <hi>Covenant</hi> with God? Nothing leſſe; for, ſo ſoon as ever the danger, the feare, the amazement at ſuch an helliſh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and the neere approach to the execution of it, was a little over; the Traitors themſelves fell not deeper into the pit of deſtruction which themſelves had digged, than generally all ſorts of men did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the gulfe of their old ſinnes, as if they owed more to <hi>Hell,</hi> than to <hi>Heaven,</hi> for ſo great a deliverance. And, is it better now? Where is the <hi>Covenant</hi> (ſuch a Covenant) with God, that ſo wonderfull a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance deſerveth, and requireth?</p>
            <p>Theſe men may pleaſe themſelves, and feed ſweetly upon a vaine dreame that there is no harme in all this; but the Apoſtle brings them in a ſad reckoning, after a ſharp chiding for it, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.4, 5, What? ſaith he, <hi>Deſpiſeſt thou the riches of his goodneſſe, and forbearance, and long ſuffering, not knowing that the goodneſſe of God leadeth thee to repentance?</hi> The end of all Gods <hi>goodneſſe</hi> in forbearing, advancing, and giving thee proſperity; and of his <hi>long ſuffering,</hi> in ſparing thee when thou haſt abuſed proſperity; and of all his mercy, in delivering thee out of adverſity; is, <hi>to lead thee to repentance;</hi> to draw thee neerer to Himſelfe, even <hi>in an everlaſting Covenant.</hi> And if it have not this effect on thee, the Apoſtle hath ſaid it, and the God of Heaven will make it good, that <hi>thou deſpiſeſt the riches of his goodneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. Thou
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65562:19"/> trampleſt all mercies under thine impure feet, when they doe not raiſe and ſcrue thee up ſo neere to thy God, as to enter a ſolemne <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with them. And, what then? Thou wilt not ſtay there, but fall into more ſinne, and under greater judgement; and, <hi>after thy hardneſſe and impenitent heart, treaſureſt up unto thy ſelfe wrath</hi> (that is, more and more <hi>wrath</hi>) againſt the <hi>day of wrath and revelation of the righteous iudgement of God.</hi> This is the end of all who make not the <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> of God, a prevailing motive thus <hi>to ioyne themſelves to the Lord;</hi> they fall into moe, and greater ſinnes, and abominations; and ſo adde daily to that great heape, and to thoſe Seas of divine wrath that hang over their heads, to overwhelme and confound them for ever.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Others, if, after ſome time of lying under the weight of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny preſſures of the Church and State, they arrive at ſome hopes and opportunities of eaſing themſelves of thoſe burdens, and of freeing the Land of the great Inſtruments of all their evils;<note place="margin">2. Of ſuch as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving meanes of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance think it enough to rid out of the way the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of their evils.</note> they conceit ſtrongly, that, if this be done, all is done. If but ſome of the <hi>Nimrods</hi> who have invaded their Lawes, and Liberties, bee pulled downe, (Which is an act of Iuſtice) how doe the <hi>Many</hi> (who doe nothing towards any Reformation of themſelves) rejoyce, and promiſe to themſelves great matters! Now (think they) there will be an end of all our miſeries, and we ſhall ſee golden dayes;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Amos</hi> 5.24.</note> 
               <hi>Iudgement ſhall run downe like waters, and righteouſneſſe like a mighty ſtreame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh Brethren! deceive not your ſelves. If this bee all you look at; if, upon opening this <hi>doore of hope,</hi> this be all you ayme at, to make uſe of the time to ſecure your ſelves againſt oppreſſors, and never think of cloſing with God; or, but think of it; you may perhaps goe farre in purſuit of your owne deſignes, in providing againſt the evils you ſigh under; and, this Parliament may do great things this way: But let mee tell you from God, that this will never doe the deed, till the <hi>Covenant</hi> wee have been all this while ſpeaking of, bee reſolved on, and ſolemnly entred into by all thoſe that expect any bleſſing from that High Aſſembly. Nor this, nor all the Parliaments in the world ſhall ever be able to make us happy in ſuch a degree at leaſt as we expect, till the Lord hath even <hi>glewed,</hi> and <hi>marryed</hi> us all unto himſelfe by mutuall Covenant.</p>
            <p>It is not onely the making of good Lawes to remove our preſent grievances; no, nor the cutting downe of all the evill Inſtruments in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65562:20"/> our State or Church at one blow, that can ſecure us againſt the like; yea, worſe evils for the future; but rather, as one wave followes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, ſo one miſchiefe will ſtill tread on the heeles of another, and greater plagues will ever crowd in after the former, till wee cloſe with God by ſuch a ſolemne Covenant.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> or <hi>Philiſtia,</hi> made themſelves marvellous merry, when any of the Governours or Kings of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> or <hi>Iudah</hi> (ſuch as <hi>Sampſon, David, Vzziah,</hi> &amp;c.) that had ſorely yoked and hampered them, were removed by death, and others come in the roome that could doe but little againſt them. When ſuch an one as <hi>Ahaz,</hi> who never wonne battaile of them, but ſtill went by the worſe, ſwayed the Scepter; oh how joyfull were the <hi>Philiſtines!</hi> But mark what a damp God caſt in among them in the midſt of all their mirth;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſai.</hi> 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>Reioyce not thou whole Paleſtina, becauſe the rod of him that ſmote thee is broken,</hi> (that <hi>Vzziah,</hi> and other Potent and ſucceſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Kings are taken away, and weake unhappy <hi>Ahaz</hi> come in the roome) <hi>for out of the Serpents root ſhall come forth a Cockatrice, and his fruit ſhall be a fiery flying ſerpent. Ahaz</hi> ſhall leave an <hi>Hezekiah</hi> behind him,<note place="margin">See 2. <hi>King.</hi> 18.8.</note> that ſhall pay all his Fathers debts upon the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and plague them yet more than all that went before him.</p>
            <p>And have not we ſeen this verified alſo neerer home? Have not ſome, in former times, beene taken away, who have been great Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors, and Inſtruments of many ſore preſſures? And, how have men rejoyced at their fals? Nor know I, why they ſhould not, if ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice in a juſt way have cut them off. But alas! what good, in the iſſue, hath followed, or can be yet hoped for ſo long as men continue <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines,</hi> enemies to God and his Church, <hi>Anti-Covenanters</hi> (even with <hi>Hell</hi>) rather than true <hi>Covenanters</hi> with God? Whether is our Condition any what better now then heretofore, when thoſe <hi>Levia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thans</hi> were alive, &amp; in their height? I appeale to your ſelves. And the reaſon of all is this, that men miſtake the meanes of Cure, or at leaſt fall ſhort of it. The cutting off of evill Doers (how neceſſary ſoever it be) is not all, nor the maine requiſite to make a people happy; unleſſe alſo there be a thorough joyning of themſelves to God by <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If you therefore that be now convened in Parliament, ſhould ſit ſo long as you deſire, even theſe 7. yeares, (if your buſineſſe ſhould require it) and think, you would make ſuch Examples of men that have violated the Lawes, and invaded your Liberties; and enact ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65562:20"/> many wholeſome Lawes to prevent the like preſumptions for the future, as ſhould put us into a new world, cauſing men to admire the happy ſtate and frame of Government which you would ſet up: yet all this would never produce the expected effect, but prove as a meer dreame of an hungry man, who <hi>in his dreame eateth</hi> aboundantly, <hi>but when he awakes, is empty;</hi> unleſſe you alſo, not onely reſolve upon, but execute this maine duty of entring <hi>Covenant</hi> with your God.</p>
            <p>Againe, thirdly, others can <hi>roare like beares,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Of ſuch as think ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary <hi>Faſting</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, without a Covenant. <hi>Jſai</hi> 59.11.</note> 
               <hi>and mourne ſore like doves,</hi> when they find themſelves diſappointed of their hopes: when Parliaments have been broken up in diſcontent, <hi>when they have look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for Iudgement, and there is none, for ſalvation, but it hath been far from them:</hi> then they have howled like dragons, not onely for affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but perhaps for ſinnes alſo, eſpecially if deliverance upon de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance hath been ſnatcht from them, even when it hath ſeemed ſo neere that they had begun to take poſſeſſion of it: yet, (ſilly men that they are!) their evils haunt them ſtill, and prevaile more and more, after all their faſtings, humblings, and ſtrong cries to God their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer. For alas! what will all this doe without a <hi>Covenant,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out taking hold of God, and <hi>ioyning themſelves</hi> to him to bee his for ever? you may ſee ſuch a ſtate of the Church as this deſcribed by <hi>Iſaiah:</hi> and good were it for us to take warning by it:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jſai.</hi> 64.6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Wee all doe fade as a leafe, and our iniquities like the wind have taken us away.</hi> And why all this? The next words will tell you: <hi>there is none that calleth upon thy Name, that ſtirreth up himſelfe to take hold of thee,</hi> ſay they to the Lord who had <hi>hid his face from them, and conſumed them for their ſins.</hi> Not that they did not at all call upon God, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did not ſo call upon him as to <hi>ſtirre up themſelves to take hold of him</hi> by Covenant; therefore is it accounted no better than a not calling upon him at all. Thus men loſe not onely their opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities of deliverances offered, but their duties alſo by which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to further it againſt another time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Some, it may bee, goe yet further. Vpon the hearing of ſuch a duty (ſo much preſſed and inculcated) they beginne to bee a little ſtirred, they are convinced that it is indeed true, ſuch a Covenant<note place="margin">4. Of ſuch as are convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the neceſſity of a Covenant, yet come not up to it. <hi>Hoſea</hi> 3.14.</note> is fit to be made: but here (like <hi>Ephraim</hi> an <hi>unwiſe ſonne) they ſtand ſtill at the breaking forth of the Children</hi> of the Covenant. They faine would, but loth they be to goe thorough with the bargaine. They beginne to come on, and then fall back againe. They are ſo long a
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65562:21"/> cheapning, treating, complementing, diſputing how ſafe it may bee for them, how well it may ſtand with their profits, projects, ends, intereſts, relations; that they coole againe, and never come up to a full reſolution. Oh, ſayes one, this is a good courſe, and fit to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: but my engagements, callings, Alliance, company, ſervice will not conſiſt with it. Another ſweares, hee could finde in his heart to make triall of it, but that he ſhould be jeered, ſcorned, and perhaps loſe his place, or hopes for it: another, he is for it, but at preſent he cannot enter upon it. Thus one thing or other ſtill keeps this duty without doores, and holds moſt men off from the work for ever.</p>
            <p>But beloved, take heed of this dallying. What ever you think, it is no better than a <hi>departing away from the living God,</hi> that ſprings from <hi>an evill heart of unbeliefe;</hi> when, being fully convinced of the weight, neceſſity, and commodity of the duty, you will yet, <hi>while it is called to day,</hi> adventure ſo farre to <hi>harden your hearts,</hi> as not to ſet upon the work inſtantly, and to go thorough with it. <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Woe unto all ſuch dodging Chriſtians; they ſhall finde to their coſt that God will write them <hi>Lo-ammi,</hi> Hoſ. 1.9. and pronounce of them, <hi>They are not my people, and I am not their God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any think, what adoe is here? what meanes this man to bee ſo earneſt? would hee have us all turne Covenanters? yes, with <hi>God.</hi> Why, what if I doe not? Then never look for good from him, how faire ſoever thy hopes be. <q rend="inline">No? ſayes another; Ile try that, ſure I have ſeene many a good day in my time, and hope to ſee more, though I never ſwallow this doctrine:</q> therefore he reſolves to go hence, as he came hither; as he lived yeſterday, ſo he will to morrow; though this day hee doe as his neighbours doe, keeping ſome order, (much againſt the will of his baſe luſts, that ring him but an harſh peale in his eare for this little abſtinence) yet to morrow he will bee for his ſwearing, drinking, whoring, any exceſſe, and riot, as much as ever; and yet, by grace of God he hopes to prove all theſe words to be but wind, and to do as well as the beſt of them all when he comes to die.</p>
            <p>But woe worth the day that ever ſuch a man was born, that when hee heares God calling him with ſo much importunity <hi>to ſtand</hi> even <hi>this very day before the Lord, to enter into Covenant with the Lord his God, and into his Oath,</hi> ſhall ſo harden his neck, and harbour ſuch <hi>a roote of gall and wormewood</hi> within his heart, as when he heares <hi>the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65562:21"/> words of the Curſe</hi> upon all thoſe that will not enter into Covenant; or, entring into it ſhall not keep it, hee <hi>ſhall bleſſe himſelfe in his heart ſaying, I ſhall have peace, though I walke in the imagination of mine heart, and adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt:</hi> See, and tremble at what God hath reſolved to do with that man, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.20, 21. <hi>The Lord will not ſpare him, but the anger of the Lord, and his iealouſie ſhall ſmoke againſt that man; and all the Curſes that are written in (Gods) Book ſhall lie upon him, and the Lord ſhall blot out his name from under heaven.</hi> Here is nothing but fury powred out, upon ſuch a wretch; not a bleſſing ſhal deſcend upon him, not a curſe ſhall eſcape and goe by him; not onely himſelf, and poſterity, but his very name (ſo far as it is an honour) ſhall all be caſt out of the world, as out of the midſt of a ſling.</p>
            <p>If hee pleaſe himſelfe with this, <q rend="inline">Yet I ſhall live as long as ſome others;</q> if they have any happineſſe, I reſolve to ſhare with them; he will find that God will not leave him ſo, <hi>but the Lord will ſeparate him unto evill out of all the Tribes of Iſrael,</hi> ſo as, though all others be ſafe; yet, as a ſtrucken Deere is unhearded from all the reſt, and followed by the dogs till he be pul'd downe and kill'd; ſo ſhall it be with this man, <hi>according to all the curſes of the Covenant, that are written in the Book of the Law.</hi> Although the whole Kingdome be ſafe, and all others in it be in peace, yet he and his houſe ſhall periſh; the line of Confuſion ſhall bee ſtretched out over him, hell and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation ſhall be his portion, how high ſoever hee now beares his head, and how much ſoever hee ſuffer his heart to ſwell againſt the truth, ſuppoſing all that he likes not, to be nothing but a ſpice of indiſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, yea of faction, and (it may bee) of Sedition; when yet nothing is offered, but what is (I truſt) pregnantly proved out of Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. So farre the firſt <hi>Vſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Vſe. Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing the chiefe cauſe why <hi>Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſe of our evills goes on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſlowly.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. This may <hi>informe</hi> us touching the true cauſe (which moſt neerely concernes our ſelves) of the ſlow proceedings of Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of things amiſſe among us, both in the Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth: Why God hath not yet given us ſo full a deliverance from <hi>Babylon;</hi> why there have been ſo many ebbings and flowings in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion, yea, more ebbings than flowings; Why generall grievances ſwell to ſuch an height, and that all opportunities of cure have vaniſhed, ſo ſoone as appeared: how it comes to poſſe that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit God hath moved the heart of the King to call Parliament af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Parliament, yet by and by, one ſpirit of diviſion or another,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65562:22"/> ſometimes from one quarter,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2.</hi> Vſe. Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſometimes from another, (like the <hi>evill ſpirit</hi> which God ſent <hi>between Abimelech, and the men of She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem,</hi> to the ruine of both) ſtill comes betweene, and blaſteth all our hopes,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.23, 24.</note> leaving us in worſe caſe than we were in before; and whence it is (in regard of our ſelves) that in ſtead of ſetting up the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Ordinances of Chriſt in more purity, there is ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary mixture, and ſuch a corrupting of all things, in Doctrine, in worſhip, in every thing; <hi>Arminianiſme, Socinianiſme</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Idolatry</hi> breaking in againe over all the Kingdome like a floud.</p>
            <p>What is a chiefe cauſe of all this? Have we not <hi>prayed?</hi> have wee not <hi>faſted?</hi> Have we not had more <hi>Faſts</hi> at <hi>Parliaments</hi> of late, than in many yeares before? Yea, hath not there been, generally among Gods people, more frequent humiliations, more frequent ſeeking of God, notwithſtanding the malice and rage of ſome men to diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and ſuppreſſe it, than in former times? Why then is Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and Reformation ſo ſlow in comming?</p>
            <p>Surely, Beloved, we have all this while miſtaken the maine buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and neglected the principall part of a Religious <hi>Faſt.</hi> You come, <hi>Faſt</hi> after <hi>Faſt,</hi> to ſeek God in his Houſe; You forbeare your victuals, afflict your ſoules, endure it out a long time; you pray, heare, confeſſe your ſinnes, and freely acknowledge, that all is juſt that God hath brought upon us, and that we ſuffer leſſe than we deſerve. All this is well. But here is the error, and the true Cauſe of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of all our evils, and of their growing greater; namely, that all this while wee have never, in any <hi>Faſt,</hi> or at any other time, entred into ſuch a ſolemne and publique <hi>Covenant</hi> with God, as his people of old have often done upon like occaſions and exigents.</p>
            <p>That I may yet more effectually bring home this to all our hearts, give mee leave briefly to parallel the ſlow pace of our deliverance out of <hi>Myſticall Babylon</hi> with that of <hi>Iudah,</hi> and ſome of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>old Babylon,</hi> which for a long time had held them Captives.</p>
            <p>And here firſt, bee pleaſed to call to minde, that, as touching the Captive <hi>Iewes,</hi> God failed not (on his part) of his promiſe. At the end of 70. yeares, liberty of returne from <hi>Babylon</hi> to <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> was proclaimed, in the firſt yeare of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the <hi>Perſian</hi> Monarch: whereupon,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.1, 2. <hi>Ezra</hi> 2.</note> many did returne, under the conduct of <hi>Zorobbabel.</hi> Being come home to Hieruſalem, wee may not conceive that they
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65562:22"/> were not at all touched with ſenſe of their deliverance, or of the ſins which had formerly provoked the Lord, to caſt them into that great bondage out of which they were delivered.</p>
            <p>Well, on they goe; firſt, to offer ſacrifices in the right place, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the foundation of the Temple of the Lord was not yet laid.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 3.6.</note> 
               <hi>In the ſecond yeare of their comming, Zorobbabel</hi> began <hi>to ſet forward the work of the houſe of the Lord,</hi> and the foundation was laid.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Verſe</hi> 8. <hi>Verſe</hi> 10. <hi>Ezra</hi> 4.1.</note> But <hi>the adverſaries of Iudah</hi> (the Great Officers of the Kingdome under the King of <hi>Perſia</hi>) apprehending, or rather pretending, the going on of this building to be matter of prejudice and danger to that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, they procure a ſtay of it, upon reaſon of State; ſo as it was well nigh an hundred yeares ere they got liberty to go on againe, and it was above an 100. yeares before the Temple could bee finiſhed. For, as many exact Chronologers obſerve, the Temple was not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected in the reigne of <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpis,</hi> as ſome have thought; but in the ſixth yeare of <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi> betweene whom and the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Darius,</hi> both <hi>Xerxes</hi> (the husband of <hi>Eſther,</hi> and called in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <hi>Ahaſhuerus</hi>) and <hi>Artaxexes Longimanus</hi> ſucceſſively ſwayed the <hi>Perſian</hi> Scepter. In all which time, many things were amiſſe; Cruelty, Oppreſſion, Adultery, Mixture with ſtrange wives, and other great deformations remained. Then comes <hi>Ezra,</hi> after the Temple was finiſhed, and ſomewhat he did, to ſet forward the work of Reformation, in the ſeventh yeare of <hi>Artaxerxes Mnemon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ezra</hi> 7.7.</note> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor to <hi>Darius Nothus.</hi> And yet, there was much more to doe. After him therefore comes <hi>Nehemiah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 1.1.</note> in the twentieth yeare of the ſame <hi>Artaxerxes Mnemon;</hi> and after all the former endeavours, he findes the Church ſtill weltring in her bloud, and even wallowing in her owne gore; I meane, in moſt of her old and long continued ſins; (although cured of Idolatry) ſo that ſtill there was great corruption in doctrine, in worſhip, and in manners.</p>
            <p>Whereupon he now reſolves, and ſets upon a more thorough Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of all theſe; but could never effect it, till beſide the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming, and holding of a publique <hi>Faſt,</hi> he and all the people lighted upon this courſe, namely, of entring into a publique and ſolemne <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant</hi> with the Lord, <hi>ſubſcribed, ſealed</hi> and <hi>ſworne</hi> unto,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. <hi>ult.</hi> and 10.29.</note> as before you have heard: and ſo, from that time forward, the work proſpered, and the Church was purged of many abominations, wherewith till that time ſhe was defiled.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:65562:23"/>
            <p>Behold here, <hi>Quantae molis erat dilectam condere Gentem,</hi> how great a work, how long a buſineſſe to perfect a Reformation even of Gods deareſt people. Their captivity in <hi>Babylon</hi> laſted not halfe ſo long time, as was ſpent after their returne thence, ere their Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could be brought to any tolerable perfection.</p>
            <p>And why ſo? Did they omit <hi>prayer,</hi> and <hi>faſting,</hi> and ſeeking ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after God? ſurely no. For, in <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.19. we read of foure ſeverall publike Faſts, (<note n="*" place="margin">Quarto menſt Vrbs fuit expugnata, quinto autem fuerat exciſum Templum &amp; conſumptum incendio: ſep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timo menſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfectus tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fuit Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doliaes, qui ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>terat cum reſidua plebe quae collectaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erat ab ejus manu. Iejuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um autem dici mi menſis pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant fuiſse in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum poſt urbem obſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam. Ergo je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junium menſis decimi, tempore alio praeceſſit, <hi>Calvin.</hi> in Loc. <hi>Non, quod haec omnia in eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem accide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runt anno, ſed diverſis annorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tervallis.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>The faſt of the fourth moneth, the faſt of the fifth moneth, the faſt of the ſeventh, and the faſt of the tenth moneth</hi>) which they held, not onely by all the time of the 70. yeeres captivitie in <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> but many yeeres after their return thence, <hi>Zach.</hi> 7.3. and <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. But all this labour was in great part loſt, for want of this addition to all their humiliation, and prayer; namely, <hi>The ioyning of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant not to be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when God once directed <hi>Nehemiah</hi> to this courſe, ſee, how all things began to thrive and come on a maine. Now, not onely the <hi>Temple,</hi> but even the <hi>walls</hi> of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> were built up, (and that within one twelve yeeres after this Covenant was ſmitten) which before lay waſt many ſcores of yeeres.</p>
            <p>Let us now reflect upon our ſelves, and the State of Religion, and progreſſe of Reformation in our owne Church, that we may make up the Parallel.</p>
            <p>Some beginnings of our deliverance from <hi>Babylon</hi> we received by King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth. For, he threw out the <hi>Pope.</hi> His ſonne King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth came after, and caſt out Popery, in the body and bulke of it. A great work, and a large ſtep, for the ſhort time of his infant reigne. And indeed, he had many excellent helps that way, (beſide the zeale of his owne pious heart) an Excellent Archbiſhop, a Prudent and vigilant Protector, beſide others; elſe he could never have done ſo much. Notwithſtanding the potency and ſecret under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minings of thoſe mighty Factions then prevailing, hindred the work not a little, ſo that it exceeded not an infant-<hi>Reformation;</hi> yea, through the immature death of that <hi>Ioſiah,</hi> it ſoone prov'd abortive.</p>
            <p>The Princeſſe that came after, quickly turn'd the Tide, before it was halfe high water: and ſhe ſet all the Gates wide open again both for Pope, and Popery to reenter with triumph, and to drink drunk of the bloud of our Anceſtors, till God diſcharged her, and releaſed his people from her crueltie.</p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:65562:23"/>
            <p>So that when Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (that glorious <hi>Deborah</hi>) mounted the Throne, although her heart was upright and loathed the Idolatry of the former Reigne, yet found ſhe worke enough to reſtore any thing at all, and to make any beginnings of a Reformation. She ſoone felt, when ſhe would have throughly pluckt up Popery both root and branch, (ſuperfluous Ceremonies, and all remaining raggs of ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition, as well as groſſe Idolatry) that ſhe had to do with an <hi>Hydra,</hi> having ſuch a ſtrong partie of ſtout Popelings to grapple with at home, and ſuch potent and dangerous abetters of them, to cope withall abroad. I need not name them. I might adde hereunto, ſome difficulties ariſing from the intereſts and engagements of not a few of thoſe (though good, and holy men) that underwent voluntary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile in the heat of the <hi>Marian</hi> perſecution; who, while they were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, had a large ſhare in the <hi>troubles at Franckford;</hi> (too eagerly, perhaps, purſuing the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Formes of <hi>Worſhip,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi>) and ſo, when upon their returne, they were advanced to places of Dignitie, and Government in this Church, they were the more apt and forward to maintaine and hold up that Cauſe wherein they had ſo farre appeared, and for which (ſome of them) with more heat than Charitie had ſo openly declared themſelves, in forrein parts. And ſo, what by one impediment, and what by another, we ſee it hath been a long time ere our Reformation can be thoroughly poliſhed and perfected, as were to be wiſhed and deſired; for there is nothing ſo perfect, here, but is capable of more perfection.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſo farre are we become now from going forward with the work, notwithſtanding the pietie &amp; care of our Princes ſince the laſt Reſtitution of Religion in this Kingdome, that (as it was in <hi>Ioſiahs</hi> time, though his owne heart were for God, yet there was a packe of rottten men, both Prieſts and People, very great pretenders to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, but indeed mad upon Images, and Idols) we begin to fall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and not onely to coaſt anew upon the brinks of <hi>Babylon,</hi> from whence we were happily delivered, but even to launch out into her deepeſt Lakes of ſuperſtition and Idolatry, under pretence of ſome extraordinary <hi>pietie of the times,</hi> and of ſome <hi>good worke in hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What is the reaſon of all this, but that (not ſo much as once) ſince the firſt beginning of Reformation of Religion in this Iſland, we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (for ought I know) entred into ſuch a ſolemne, publique,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65562:24"/> univerſall <hi>Covenant</hi> to be the Lords, as he requireth for thoſe begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings already given us; but have ſate looſe from God, and ſo have not joyned together as one man, zealouſly to propugne his trueth and Ordinances, and to ſtand by him and his Cauſe, as becomes the people of God, in all juſt and warrantable wayes, againſt all oppoſers and gainſayers.</p>
            <p>So long as we pleaſe our ſelves in this liberty of our holding off from a Covenant with God, we may feed our ſelves with vaine hopes of redreſſe of things amiſſe, but ſhall ſpeed no better than thoſe libertines &amp; back-ſliders in <hi>Ier.</hi> 14. who lookt for great matters from God, but came ſhort of all, and then ſeemed to wonder at the reaſon. For, thus they beſpeake him, ver. 8. <hi>O the hope of Iſrael, the Saviour thereof in time of trouble, why ſhouldeſt thou be as a ſtranger in the Land, and as a wayfaring man, that turneth aſide to tarry</hi> (onely) <hi>for a night? Why ſhouldſt thou be as a man aſtonied, as a mightie man that cannot ſave? yet thou O Lord, art in the midſt of us, and we are called by thy name.</hi> See here how they are put to it. They acknowledge his Power, Goodneſſe, Preſence, yet they are not ſaved. He ſeemes to be like <hi>Sampſon,</hi> with his Locks cut off, as if he were not able to ſave, or would not do it: and this they wonder and ſtand amazed at, as a thing incredible, and impoſſible.</p>
            <p>But God makes them a ſhort and ſharp anſwer, (which may alſo ſerve us) ver. 10. <hi>Thus,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>have they loved to wander, they have not refrained their feet; therefore the Lord doth not accept them.</hi> If God be as <hi>a wayfaring</hi> man; ſometimes with a people, more often gone from them; ſometimes bleſſing, ſometimes croſſing them, and ſuffering them to fall under heavy preſſures, &amp; never keeps an even and ſetled ſtation or courſe of proceeding with them, it is but that he hath learnt from themſelves (as I may ſo ſpeake:) they will be their owne men; they will not be tyed to him ſo ſtrictly; they will have ſome libertie for their luſts, for the world, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, for any thing: and loe here is the fruit of it, God will not be bound to, nor walke with them; he will not draw out that ſtrength, that goodneſſe, that compaſſion which might deliver them from the evils they howle under; He will neither heare them, nor any body elſe for them; not <hi>Ieremy</hi> himſelfe, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11. not <hi>Noah, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Iob, Ezek.</hi> 14. Nothing therefore, but a more ſolemne and ſtrict Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, will put us into a poſture and condition capable of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65562:24"/> perfect redreſſe of our grievances, how faire ſo ever either now,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Vſe. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> or hereafter, we may ſeeme to be for it. This is the ſecond uſe.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>ſuffer,</hi> I beſeech you, a few <hi>words of exhortation.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning Iewes (you ſee) call upon all their Nation to enter into <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant.</hi> Give me leave then, to call upon You the <hi>Repreſentative Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of this whole Kingdome who ſtand here before the Lord this day to humble your ſoules; and let me alſo prevaile with you all, to <hi>ioyne your ſelues,</hi> even this day, <hi>to the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> Make this day, a day indeed, a day of <hi>Covenan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> with God, and God ſhall Covenant with you, and make it the beginning of more happineſſe than ever you yet enjoyed.</p>
            <p>Beloved, miſtake me not, my meaning extends not to engage you in any <hi>Civill Covenant</hi> and <hi>Bond</hi> for defence of your Municipall Lawes and Liberties. No doubt you will be able to find meanes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>now (by the bleſſing of God) to ſetle thoſe things, in a legall way; eſpecially if you be carefull to Covenant with God. Much leſſe is it my purpoſe to draw you into that late <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Oath and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant</hi> (enjoyned by the late <hi>Canon</hi>) which in my apprehenſion is little leſſe than a Combination and Conſpiracy againſt both King and State. My buſineſſe is, meerely to perſwade you into a <hi>Religious Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God,</hi> as himſelfe hath preſcribed and commanded; and, his people, in the beſt times of Reformation, have readily admitted: namely, every man to ſtirre up himſelfe and to lift up his Soule to take hold of God to be glued and united to him, in all faithfulneſſe, ſincerity, care, and diligence, to be onely his for ever.</p>
            <p>This if we doe, we need not care much for other Covenants: God will provide for that, and make a league for us even with the <hi>beaſts of the field,</hi> and with the <hi>ſtones of the ſtreet;</hi> he will <hi>make</hi> our <hi>Exactors peace,</hi> and our <hi>Officers righteouſneſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.17, 18.</note> violence <hi>ſhall no more be heard in the Land, nor waſting, nor deſtruction within our borders;</hi> our very <hi>walls</hi> ſhall be <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and our <hi>Gates praiſe.</hi> He will be a God of Covenants, and take care for our eſtates, Lawes, liberties, lives, children and all that belong to us, when once this is done.</p>
            <p>Therefore I beſeech you, yea I require you in the name of the God of heaven, whoſe you are, whom you ſerve, before whom you ſtand, &amp; from whom you expect ſalvation in the midſt of the Earth, as well as in Heaven, that you forthwith enter into this bond. Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65562:25"/> no aſſiſtance, no ſucceſſe in any of your Conſultations, in any Lawes that you agree upon, till you have fully brought your hearts to this point, to follow the Lord fully; to be no more for your ſelves than you would have the deareſt wife of your boſome to bee for any other man in the world; but to be wholly for the Lord, to imploy &amp; improve all your wit, abilities, induſtry, counſels, actions, eſtate, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 17.10.</note> and lives to promote his ſervice &amp; honour, what ever become of your ſelves and yours for doing of it. Say not as ſome Ieerers (of whom it is hard to judge whether their malice or ignorance bee the greater) doe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 50.5.</note> that there needs no more Covenants than what wee made in Baptiſme, and that all other Covenants ſavour ſtrongly of faction, and the Puritan Leaven. For, ſo Gods people of old made a <hi>Covenant</hi> by <hi>Circumciſion,</hi> and after by <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> that is, in every <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> which they offered, they did renew their Covenant begun in <hi>Circumciſion.</hi> Nevertheleſſe, God thought it neceſſary often to call them out to ſtrike another ſolemne Covenant with him beſides the former.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 19.</note> You have already heard, that ſo ſoone as the Iſraelites were gone out of Egypt, and entred a little way in the wilderneſſe, hee put them upon a <hi>Covenant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.</note> When he brought them neer to <hi>Canaan,</hi> he required another ſolemne <hi>Covenant</hi> of them. And when <hi>Ioſhuah</hi> had brought them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> and divided to each of them the lot of his inheritance, hee drew them into another ſolemne <hi>Covenant, Ioſh.</hi> 24. So that here was Covenant upon Covenant, and yet can no man (without blaſphemy) charge it with any Puritan humour, facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or any thing ſuperfluous or uncomely for the Greateſt on earth to ſubmit unto.</p>
            <p>That I may a little more enforce this duty, and quicken you to the imbracing of it, give mee leave to preſent you with ſome <hi>Motives</hi> further to preſſe you to it, and with ſome few <hi>Directions</hi> to guide you in it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. For, <hi>Motives.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Motives</hi> to a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant. 1. Our many <hi>Deliverances.</hi>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider 1. how many, great, admirable, and even miraculous deliverances God hath given us; What great things hee hath done for us. No Nation under heaven can ſay more to his praiſe, in this kinde; than we have cauſe to do. Our Great deliverances out of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> from the <hi>Spaniſh Invaſion,</hi> from the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi> and from many other evils and feares, do all call upon you for a Covenant. Yea, even the preſent Mercy and Opportunity of opening that An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65562:25"/> Regular and Approved Way of cure of thoſe publique evils that threaten confuſion and deſolation to all,<note place="margin">3. <hi>Vſe. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Motives.</note> pleades hard for the ſame duty. But among all theſe, I deſire You of that Great and honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Body of the Parliament, to reflect ſadly upon that Stupendious Deliverance from the <hi>Gun-powder Treaſon,</hi> which more eſpecially and immediately was bent againſt You. For, albeit the ruine of the whole Kingdome was in their Eye who were the Curſed Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Antichriſt, and of the Devill his Father, in that helliſh De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne; yet no blow could have come at us, but through Your ſides. And, albeit ſome of You that have the honour to be members of this preſent Parliament, were then unborne; yet had that Plot taken ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, ſcarce any of You had been this day in being, to have ſate there now, but had long ſince been covered and buried under the aſhes of confuſion. Think now, whether ſuch a preſervation deſerve leſſe at Your hands, than to give Your ſelves to your Great Deliverer, for ſo Great a Deliverance, whereby three Nations deſtinated at once to Death, received no leſſe than a joyfull reſurrection from the Dead, and were againe <hi>borne at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, let not this Great mercy ſeeme ſmall in Your eyes. And remember too, that you may have as much need of God ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time: nay, you know not what need You may have of him this preſent Parliament. You cannot be ignorant of the many murmures and more than whiſperings of ſome deſperate and devilliſh con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception ſuſpected to bee now in the wombe of the Ieſuiticall fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: And how neere it may bee to the birth, or how prodigious it may prove being borne, I take not upon me to divine: but this we are all ſure of, that what ever it be which they are big withall, it ſhall not want the leaſt graine of the utmoſt extremity of malice and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe that all the wit, power, and induſtry of Hell it ſelfe can contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute unto it; and that they labour, as a woman in travaile, to be ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily delivered of it.</p>
            <p>What dangers, and what cauſe of feare there may bee at the preſent, I leave to your Wiſedome to conſider. But this bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident of, if Deliverances already received can prevaile with you for a <hi>Covenant,</hi> that Covenant will be your ſecurity; for it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly engage all the power and wiſdome of the Great and only wiſe God of heaven and earth to be on your ſide for ever. So that if God himſelfe have power enough, wiſdome enough, and care enough, you
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65562:26"/> cannot miſcarry; <hi>no weapon that is formed againſt you ſhall proſper,</hi> no plot, <hi>no gates of hell ſhall prevaile againſt you.</hi> And, if he have goodnes enough, mercy enough, bowells enow in him, he will then alſo raine downe aboundance of truth, righteouſneſſe, juſtice, peace and plentie upon all Corners of the Land, from whence, and on whoſe errand, You are now come together. Therefore it becomes you, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all others, to be firſt in a <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider that, till we do this, there cannot be ſuch a full enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God,<note place="margin">2. There can be no full enjoying of God, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</note> as otherwiſe there might be. Indeed, the perfect fruition of God is not to be expected till we come to heaven, but yet we might have much more of God, even in this life, than now we have, could we be perſwaded to ſuch a <hi>Covenant</hi> with him.</p>
            <p>Whatſoever experience we have of him now in any deliverance beſtowed, it would be doubled, if, upon the deliverance received, we would thus be <hi>ioyned</hi> to him. Nor is this a notion or conceit onely, but a reall trueth.</p>
            <p>For, marke what He ſaith to his people, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 19, 20. <hi>I will marry thee unto me for ever,</hi> I <hi>will betroath the unto me in righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe, and in Iudgement, and in loving kindneſſe, and in mercies,</hi> I <hi>will even marry thee unto me in faithfullneſſe, and thou ſhalt know the Lord.</hi> He that enters into Covenant with God, is <hi>betroathed,</hi> yea e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven <hi>married</hi> to him: And how married? even to the partaking of all his goods, of all he hath, yea of himſelfe, and of all that he is. As the wife may ſay,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 31.43.</note> 
               <hi>Vbi tu Caius, ego Caia;</hi> and, as <hi>Laban</hi> ſometimes, of <hi>Iacobs</hi> wives, children, and cattell, <hi>Theſe daughters are my daughters, and theſe children are my children, and theſe cattell are my cattell, and all that thou ſeeſt are mine:</hi> So a man once <hi>married</hi> to the Lord by <hi>Covenant,</hi> may without arrogancy ſay, this <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> is my righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, this <hi>iudgement</hi> is my judgement, this <hi>loving kindneſſe, theſe mercies, this faithfullneſſe</hi> which I ſee in thee, and all that thou haſt is mine, for my comfort, ſupply, ſupport, direction, ſalvation, and what not?</p>
            <p>And take notice of that phraſe, <hi>Thou ſhalt know the Lord.</hi> Did they not <hi>know</hi> him before? Yes; but never in ſuch a manner, with ſuch a <hi>Knowledge,</hi> at leaſt in ſuch a meaſure. They ſhall now know him in ſuch neere, familiar, ſweet and ineffable expreſſions of his deereſt, deepeſt, choyceſt conjugal love, as they never taſted, nor could taſte of before.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:65562:26"/>
            <p>We know how it is with a wife married to a loving husband. They loved one another before marriage, and many expreſſions of a ſpeciall love paſſed betweene them, but they never enjoyed one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother fully till the marriage was ſolemnized. Then, there is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a more intimate manifeſtation of fervent, intire, loyall, chaſte love; but a further enlarging and ſtretching out of mutuall affections to each other, than they could poſſibly have beleeved they ſhould ever have reached unto, till now experience aſſure them of it. And even thus it is between us and God. Is he good in deliverances? have we taſted of his love already? Oh how great would his goodneſſe be, how full of grace, mercy, bountie; and, how would he communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate even whole rivers of all theſe to that Soule that would once come up to him, and cloſe with him in an <hi>everlaſting Covenant! All the wayes of the Lord are mercy and trueth, unto ſuch as</hi> (make, and) <hi>keep Covenant with him, Pſal.</hi> 25.19.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider that what ever worke God calls You to,<note place="margin">3. No buck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to the worke God calls us unto, without a Covenant.</note> Yee will never buckle thoroughly to it, till you have entered into <hi>Covenant</hi> with him. An apprentiſe boy when he goes to a Maſter upon tryall onely, his minde is now on, then off againe; ſometimes he could like the trade, by and by his minde hangs after his Mother at home, or af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſome other courſe of life, and he never ſets cloſe to his buſineſſe, till he be bound. When once the Indentures be ſealed, and he enrol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, he knowes there is now no more time to deliberate; but he muſt fall to his buſineſſe, or elſe take what happens for his idleneſſe and negligence. So is it with a wife; if ſhe be but onely promiſed, or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troathed to a man, ſhe may come to his houſe, and caſt an eye up and downe; but it is rather to obſerve, than to act: ſhe may perhaps caſt out a word now and then ſomewhat freely alſo; but ſhe never ſets her ſelfe to guide the houſe, or to doe any thing to purpoſe, till ſhe be married: then, <hi>ſhe careth for the things of the world;</hi> that is, with all poſſible diligence looking to,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.34.</note> and managing of the buſineſſe of the family committed to her, <hi>how ſhe may pleaſe her huſband:</hi> all her thoughts, care, diligence run this way; ſhe makes it her buſines that ſhe muſt ſticke unto, and daily manage as a part of the marriage Covenant. And thus alſo it will be with you. You have much worke under your hands, and are like to have more; and I hope you deſire to doe all in truth of heart, for God, and not for ends of your owne: but let me tell you this will never be done througly, till once you be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65562:27"/> 
               <hi>marryed</hi> to him by ſolemne <hi>Covenant.</hi> Then will you <hi>care indeed for the things of the Lord, how you may pleaſe the Lord,</hi> in every cauſe, in every Anſwer to any Petition, and in every Vote of any Bill, or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence. You would then thinke, when you come to manage, debate, vote, any Queſtion, <q rend="inline">I am the Lords, not mine own, not my friends; will this I doe, ſtand with my Covenant? will it pleaſe God? will it be profitable for the State? is it agreeable to Iuſtice and equitie?</q> Then on with it, no man ſhall divert, or take me off But, till then, one will intreate for his friend, another for his; one will make you one way, another will draw you another way; and they both are your friends, and you know not how to deny either: and thus are you even torne in peeces betweene them, in ſo much as you ſometimes reſolve to be abſent, or to ſit ſtill and ſay nothing; or, to gratifie him that hath moſt power with You, be the cauſe what it will. But when once the Covenant is ſealed, all this will be at an end, You will quickly ſtop your eares againſt all perſwaſions that may hinder Iuſtice and Reformation; and, when this is knowne, men will ſoone forbeare alſo to trouble You with ſuch ſolicitations.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Wicked men Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Hell. <hi>Iſay.</hi> 28.</note>Againe fourthly; Wicked men ſticke not at a <hi>Covenant with death and hell</hi> it ſelfe, ſo they may but ſatisfie their Luſts; though they know the end thereof will be damnation. Oh then ſhall not we much more make a <hi>Covenant</hi> with our <hi>God</hi> to doe his will, which will be beneficiall and comfortable both here and hereafter, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure a full torrent of his mercies, bountie, grace, and eternall life, to flow in upon us!</p>
            <p n="5">5. Conſider that the Devell himſelfe will have a <hi>Covenant</hi> from all his vaſſals<note place="margin">5. The Devill himſelfe will do no great matters for his vaſſals without a Covenant.</note> that expect any extraordinary matters from him; elſe, he will not be engaged to be at their Command. There is not a Witch that hath the Devill at her beck, but ſhe muſt ſeale a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to him, ſometimes with her bloud, ſometimes by other rites and devices, and perhaps he muſt ſucke her too (as in thoſe helliſh bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaines you know they uſe;) and then, he is for her, during the time agreed upon. And ſhall we think God will be ſo cheape, as to be (with reverence be it ſpoken) at our Command, to help, direct, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, deliver and ſave us, who will not doe ſo much for him as Witches and Sorcerers will doe for the Devill?</p>
            <p>In the 45. of <hi>Iſay,</hi> verſ. 11. there is a ſtrong expreſſion this way;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65562:27"/> 
               <hi>Thus ſaith the Lard, the Holy One of Iſrael, and his Maker, aske of mee things to come concerning my ſonnes, and concerning the work of my hands Command yee mee.</hi> It is not to be thought that God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plementeth with his people, but is free and hearty in the expreſſion of what they ſhall really find him. But mark; it <hi>concernes his Sonnes;</hi> that is, thoſe that are truely in Covenant with him. This priviledge is for none elſe. So that the way to have God at <hi>Command,</hi> (with humility be it uſed) is to bee his <hi>ſonnes</hi> and <hi>daughters</hi> by <hi>Covenant.</hi> For, to whom it is ſaid, <hi>I will be their God, and they ſhall bee my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,</hi> to them is it ſpoken, <hi>I will bee a father unto you, and yee ſhall bee my ſonnes and daughters, ſaith the Lord Almighty,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.18. And to them he ſaith alſo, <hi>Command ye me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. Conſider that it is the proper and chiefe buſineſſe of a <hi>Faſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. This is the proper worke of a Religious Faſt. <hi>Nehem.</hi> 9.</note> to enter into <hi>Covenant</hi> with God. You ſee it to bee the practiſe of the Church in <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> time. And where this hath been omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the <hi>Faſt</hi> hath been loſt. God never accounted any of thoſe foure annuall ſolemne <hi>Faſts</hi> before mentioned, that were ſo long in uſe among the Iewes, to be <hi>faſts unto him;</hi> but calls them, <hi>faſts to themſelves,</hi> Zach. 7.5, 6. Why, but becauſe they looked no further in their Faſts, but <hi>to afflict their ſoules for a day,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſay</hi> 58.</note> 
               <hi>to bow downe their heads as a bullruſh, and to ſpread ſack-cloth and aſhes under them,</hi> and there an end. But they loſt all their labour, getting nothing from God but a chiding and contempt.</p>
            <p>And in truth, when will wee thus <hi>ioyne</hi> our ſelves to the Lord, if not at a <hi>Faſt?</hi> Then, are our hearts in more than ordinary tune for ſuch a work, when wee are brought to ſet our ſinnes before us, and humbly to confeſſe, bewaile and renounce them; when wee have taken ſome paines with our Soules to ſoften, and melt them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord; eſpecially if then they be in any meaſure raiſed up to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Him, with any apprehenſion of his love in the pardon of ſo many and great ſinnes, even when the Soule is moſt caſt downe for them. Then, I ſay, ſtrike through the Covenant, or it will never be. If you let ſlip this opportunity, you may perhaps never obtaine the like while you live; but either your ſelves may bee cut off, or your hearts ſhut up in deſperate hardneſſe, like unto <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> whom eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deliverance, and new experience of Gods favour in taking off new evils, hardened more, and made worſe.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In the laſt place (and let it not have the leaſt force of perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion)
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65562:28"/> remember and conſider that this day, even this very day, the 17. of <hi>November,</hi> 82. yeares ſithence, began a new reſurrection of this Kingdome from the dead, our ſecond happy reformation of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion by the auſpitious entrance of our late Royall <hi>Deborah</hi> (worthy of eternall remembrance and honour) into her bleſſed and glorious Reigne;<note place="margin">7. This very Day began the ſecond Reformation of Religion.</note> and that, from thenceforth Religion thrived, and proſpered under her Governement with admirable ſucceſſe, againſt a whole world of oppoſitions from Popiſh factors at home and abroad: So as the very Gates of hell were never able to extinguiſh that Light, which God by her meanes hath ſet up amongſt us.</p>
            <p>Conſider I beſeech you, that it is not without a ſpeciall Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, that this your meeting was caſt upon this very day (for, I preſume, little did you think of the 17. of <hi>November,</hi> when you firſt fixed on this day for your <hi>Faſt;</hi>) that, even from thence, one ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer might bee borrowed to drive home this nayle of Exhortation; that the very memory of ſo bleſſed a work begun on this very day, might throughly inflame you with deſire to enter into a <hi>Covenant;</hi> and ſo, to go forward to perfect that happy Reformation, which yet in many parts lies unpoliſhed and unperfect.</p>
            <p>Oh ſuffer not that <hi>doore of hope</hi> by Her ſet open this day, to bee againe ſhut, for want of a <hi>Covenant.</hi> If you would indeed honour Her precious memory; yea, honour God and your ſelves, and not onely continue the poſſeſſion of what ſhe (as a moſt glorious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duit pipe) hath tranſmitted to us, but perfect the work, ſet upon this duty of <hi>ioyning your ſelves to the Lord in an everlaſting Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant that ſhall not be forgotten.</hi> And ſo have you the <hi>Motives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Meanes</hi> how to enter into Covenant.</note>2. I ſhall now ſhut up all with ſome few <hi>Directions</hi> to help us in it. And here, paſſing by what hath been already ſpoken touching the <hi>preparatives</hi> to it, the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it, and the <hi>properties</hi> required in it, I ſhall onely give you theſe ſixe ſubſequent <hi>Directions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Give a Bill of divorce to all your Luſts,<note place="margin">1. Give a Bill of Divorce to all your Luſts.</note> or kill them out right. This Covenant is a marriage Covenant, and there is no marrying with God, ſo long as your former husband, your baſe corruptions, your ſwearing, riot, drunkenneſſe, uncleanneſſe, pride, oppreſſion, and what ever elſe your ſoules <hi>know to bee the plague of your owne hearts,</hi> remaine alive and undivorced. <hi>For the woman which hath an husband, is bound by the Law to her husband ſo long as hee liveth;</hi> but if he be once <hi>dead, ſhe is free from that Law,</hi> Rom. 7. Therefore
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65562:28"/> ſend theſe packing, in the firſt place.<note place="margin">3. <hi>Vſe. Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> Meanes.</note> A wiſe man will never marry a ſtrumpet, nor with any woman that hath another husband; his wife that ſhall bee onely his owne, none elſe ſhall have intereſt in her. Much leſſe then, will the Holy and Iealous God admit of any Spouſe that is wedded to any luſt, and ſo continueth. Say then, what wilt thou now doe? wilt thou ſtill keepe thy darling luſt? Haſt thou been a ſwearer, and ſo thou wilt be? a drunkard, and an uncleane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, an oppreſſour, a prophane <hi>Eſau,</hi> and wilt be ſo ſtill? Know, that God will none of thee, but abhorres all ſuch as thou art. He will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit none into Covenant but ſuch as <hi>touch not the uncleane thing, but ſeparate</hi> from it. To them onely it is, that hee promiſeth,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.</note> 
               <hi>I will bee their God, and they ſhall be my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. More eſpecially purge out and caſt away (as <hi>a Menſtruous cloth</hi>) all <hi>Idols</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. More eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally caſt out all <hi>Idols</hi> and <hi>Idolatry. Pſal.</hi> 5.4.</note> in particular. All our Luſts are lothſome to his ſtomach, but nothing is ſo abominable to his Soule, as <hi>Idolatry.</hi> This is that ſpirituall whoredome which meritoriouſly diſſolves the marriage bond where it is already knit, and lies as a barre in the way to a Covenant with God, where yet it is not made.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.4. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 17.</note> This was it for which the Lord proceeded ſo ſeverely, firſt againſt the ten Tribes, and then againſt the reſidue, as you all know. For this, the Land ſpew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them out. And where ever God promiſeth to recall them, hee uſually premiſeth this, (which ſhould firſt be done) <hi>From all your Idols will I cleanſe you, Ezek.</hi> 36.25. <hi>Ephraim alſo ſhall ſay, What have I to doe any more with Idols? Hoſ.</hi> 14.8. and all ſhall caſt them away with deteſtation, ſaying, <hi>Get thee hence,</hi> Iſai. 30.22.</p>
            <p>Every Idol is that great <hi>Image of Iealouſie,</hi> which the Lord can by no meanes endure, and which will certainly bee the deſtruction of King and People, where ever it is entertained, eſpecially if againe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived in, after it hath been once ejected. A ſad example whereof we have in <hi>Iudah,</hi> where, after <hi>Ioſiah had taken away all the abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions out of all the countries that pertained to Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.33.</note> 
               <hi>and made all that were preſent in Iſrael to ſerve the Lord onely,</hi> the Act of Reſumption of Idols and Idolatry by the ſucceeding Kings (although it is proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they did it onely <hi>ſecretly</hi> like thoſe in 2 <hi>King</hi> 17.9.) became the ruine of thoſe Kings, and Kingdomes.</p>
            <p>Beloved, let mee ſpeake freely, for I ſpeake for God, and for all your ſafeties. You cannot bee ignorant of the groſſe Idolatry daily encreaſing among us, and committed not (as adultery) in Corners
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:65562:29"/> onely, but in the open light; people going to, and comming from the Maſſe in great multitudes, and that as ordinarily, openly, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently as others goe to and from our Churches. And I doubt not but ſome of you doe know the number of Maſſes to exceed that of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</p>
            <p>Whoſe heart bleeds not over this prodigious growth of Popery, and over-flowing of Popiſh Maſſes? Who knowes not, that in the Maſſe is committed the moſt abominable Idolatry that ever the Sun beheld in the Chriſtian world? Who remembers not with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and horror, how often that inſatiable Idol hath bathed it ſelfe in the bloud of many of our Anceſtors and Progenitors? And can any be ſo ſilly as to beleeve, that it will reſt ſatisfied till it ſwim againe in our bloud alſo, unleſſe we will joyne with Idolaters, and ſo periſh in Hell? For what ever ſome men talke of the poſſibility of the ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſome perſons in that Church, (as they call it) yet it is agreed on all hands, among us, that for thoſe of our owne Nation and once of our owne Church where the light hath ſo long ſhined in ſo much brightneſſe, ſo as they have both received and profeſſed it; if they ſhall (whether to gratifie a Parent, a wife, husband, friend, Maſter, &amp;c.) put out their owne eyes, and returne back to <hi>Babylon</hi> from whence they were once ſet free, their caſe is very deſperate and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.</note> and <hi>it had been better for them never to have knowne the way of righteouſneſſe, then after they have knowne it to turne from the holy Commandement once delivered unto them.</hi> Therefore I beſeech you to take care of theſe above others.</p>
            <p>Nor ſpeak I this, onely to prevent a publique toleration, (which I hope, through the care of our pious King, and your diligence, our eyes ſhall never ſee) but to put on Authority to the utter rooting out of that abomination,<note place="margin">2 <hi>King</hi> 17.9.</note> although committed in ſecret, and with conni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vence onely.</p>
            <p>If then you will not halt between Two opinions, if you will bee thorough for God, and follow him fully, downe with all <hi>Idols</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> through the Kingdome, ſo farre as the making of the Lawes yet more ſtrict and full for that purpoſe, may effect it. Till then, you may, if you will, talke of a <hi>Covenant,</hi> and think to doe great matters: but that Great God who is ſo jealous of his glory in that, above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, will abhorre all Covenants with you. And if you, having now ſuch opportunity and power, ſhall not throughly cleanſe the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65562:29"/> Land of theſe ſpirituall whoredomes ſo boldly facing and even out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facing the glorious Goſpell profeſſed among us; bee ſure, that, in ſtead of a bleſſing upon your Conſultations and proceedings, you will draw downe a Curſe that will cleave to you, and goe home with you, and ſcatter like poyſon over all parts and Corners of the whole Kingdom, till all be utterly conſumed and become a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</p>
            <p>You all I think, agree upon the neceſſity of a great Reformation. Where ſhould you begin then, but where God ever begins? Looke into the Stories of <hi>Aſa, Jehoſaphat, Hezekiah, Joſiah,</hi> and even of <hi>Manaſſeh</hi> himſelfe, (the groſſeſt Idolater and moſt bloudy Tyrant that ever reigned in <hi>Iudah</hi>) when once God had throughly humb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him; and you ſhall ever finde that they began their grand Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation at <hi>Idols,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry</hi> committed with them. I ſpeake not this to back or countenance any tumultuous or ſeditious ſpirits that have lately been ſtirred up to do things without Commiſſion; but to You, whom God hath duely called to the work, and indiſpenſib<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly requires it at your hands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Execute true judgment</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. Execute true Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Iſa 58.6</note> and Iuſtice. <hi>Looſe the band of wickednes, undoe the heavie burdens, let the oppreſſed goe free, and break every yoke</hi> of the oppreſſor. This is a maine part of an acceptable <hi>Faſt,</hi> and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore muſt bee performed of all that will enter into Covenant with God. And this was part of Gods Anſwer to the Iewes enquiring of the Prophet whether they ſhould continue their ſolemne Faſts? <hi>Zach.</hi> 7. Therefore herein deale impartially and throughly, for here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Throne it ſelfe is eſtabliſhed. It is true, a difference muſt be put between thoſe that are only led on in evill wayes by others, and thoſe that are leaders of others: but it becomes not me to preſcribe to you in this caſe, your owne wiſdome will teach you that. Only I am to pray you, that if you ſhall find any eſcapes to have bin made in the ordinary Courts of Iuſtice, in the condigne puniſhment of <hi>Murder,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> take notice of them, and there bee ſure to ſtrike home, as <hi>Samuel</hi> did where <hi>Saul</hi> himſelfe had been too indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. There is nothing makes you ſuch faire Images of God (in the relation you now ſtand) as due execution of Iuſtice and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Therefore, if you will indeed enter into a Covenant, let this be done.<note place="margin">4. Draw others alſo.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Do your beſt to draw as many as you can the ſame way. Parents
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65562:30"/> and Maſters are bound to take care that their children and families do feare, and ſerve God, as well as themſelves. And you who now appeare before him in behalfe of the kingdome, as you muſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into a Covenant for them as well as for your ſelves, ſo muſt you do your utmoſt that they alſo for themſelves may paſſe under the ſame Covenant, with you. The repreſentative Body of Iſrael that ſtood before the Lord to make a Covenant, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29.15. made it not onely for themſelves and ſuch as were preſent, but for all that were <hi>abſent</hi> alſo. And <hi>Ioſiah</hi> when he entred into a Covenant him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, he not only cauſed <hi>all that were preſent of Iudah at the houſe of the Lord,</hi> to ſtand to it, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 34.32. But he <hi>made all Iſrael to ſerve, even to ſerve the Lord their God, ver.</hi> 33. that is, to ſtrike a Covenant with him. Therefore take care that all others, when you returne home, may make a Covenant before the Lord to walk after him in all his Commandements: that God may be ſet up more and more, and the hearts of all men may bee lifted up in the wayes of the Lord to take hold of his Covenant alſo. If you do not this, you do nothing: more is required at your hands, than of private perſons, who yet are bound to call upon others (as the men in my Text) ſaying, <hi>Come and let us joyne our ſelves unto the Lord in an everlaſting Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Would you have this to be done, namely, that all ſhould <hi>appeare before God in Zion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">5. Set up way-markes to Zion.</note> for this purpoſe? Then ſet up <hi>Way-markes</hi> to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect them thither. Take ſpeciall care that the Ordinances of God be ſet up, and held up, in more purity and plenty. Down at once with all inventions and fancies of men, which corrupt and adulterate the pure worſhip of God. Let none but He be worſhipped, and let no worſhip be thruſt upon him which himſelfe hath not preſcribed. Herein eſpecially (yet ſtill within your bounds) be zealous, and quit your ſelves like men.</p>
            <p>Above all, take better order for the more frequent, and better per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance, and due countenancing of that now vilified (but highly neceſſary) Ordinance of Preaching, which, albeit it be Gods own arme and power unto ſalvation, is yet brought into ſo deepe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt (and by none more than by thoſe who ſhould labour moſt to hold up the honour of it) that it is made a matter of ſcorne, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the odious Character of a <hi>Puritan,</hi> to be an aſſiduous Preacher. Yea, ſo farre have ſome men runne mad this way, that it is held a crime deſerving Cenſure in the higheſt Eccleſiaſticall Court in this
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65562:30"/> Kingdome, to tell but a few Clergie men out of a Pulpit, that it is an eſſentiall part of the Office of a Biſhop, to Preach<note n="*" place="margin">But <hi>ab ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio</hi> it was not ſo. The third part of the <hi>Hom.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the perill of I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatry, ſpeaking of the Biſhops of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times ſaith, that They were then Preach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing Biſhops, &amp; more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſeene in pulpits than in Princes Palaces, more often occupied in his Legacy, who ſaid, go ye into the whole world, and preach the Goſpell to all men, than in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſages and affaires of Princes of this world, <hi>p.</hi> 59. edit. 1623.</note>. Some of you know t at I belye them not.</p>
            <p>And is it not then high time to vindicate the honour of Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from thoſe virulent and ſcurrilous tongues and pens, that have of late dayes (more than ever) blaſphem'd this Ordinance; and to take more pitie of the many darke and barren parts of this king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, where many ſcarce have a Sermon in ſeven yeeres; nay ſome (as divers of worth doe credibly report) not in their whole lives? Hath not God himſelfe ſaid plainly,<note n="a" place="margin">Pro. 29.18</note> 
               <hi>Where there is no viſion the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple periſh?</hi> Is it not his owne complaint,<note n="b" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.6.</note> 
               <hi>My people are deſtroyed for lacke of knowledge?</hi> And how ſo? thus; <hi>for a long ſeaſon Iſrael had been without a teaching Prieſt, and without the Law,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 15.3. And mark too, that while they had no teaching Prieſt they were <hi>without the true God</hi> alſo. For, there is no comming at the <hi>true God,</hi> in the ordinary way, but by a <hi>teaching Priest.</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Rom. 10.14</note> 
               <hi>How</hi> ſhall they heare without a Preacher? And<note n="d" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.2</note> 
               <hi>it pleaſeth God by the fooliſhneſſe of preaching to ſave them that beleeve:</hi> and<note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> 
               <hi>faith comes by hearing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore I dare pronounce, that while ſo many thouſands with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kings Dominions, eſpecially in <hi>England, Wales,</hi> and <hi>Ireland, are ſtill</hi> ſuffered to <hi>ſit in ſuch darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death,</hi> and ſo to periſh for ever for want of conſtant, ſound, profitable Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it is impoſſible that they ſhould be capable of a Covenant with God; or, that it may be truly ſaid, that the maine body of theſe king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes are in caſe to make a Covenant with him; unleſſe you, the repreſentative Body thereof, take more care than ever yet hath been taken in this behalfe.</p>
            <p>I know the many plea's of many idle droanes and mercileſſe men to excuſe and defend an unpreaching, or ſeldome-preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; but all their fig-leaves are too ſhort to cover their own ſhame, and the nakedneſſe of thoſe poore periſhing people whom ſuch men make naked, to their own deſtruction alſo.</p>
            <p>To tell us, that preaching indeed is neceſſary for the planting of a Church, but not ſo afterwards: is nothing but to bewray their owne ſottiſh ignorance. Is not the word preached,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.2. Eph. 4. Iam. 1.18. 1 Pet. 1.23.</note> the <hi>milke</hi> and food whereby men are, and muſt be continually nouriſhed <hi>to grow</hi> up in the body of Chriſt, as well as the <hi>Seed</hi> whereof they are firſt begotten unto Chriſt? And can men that are borne, and living,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65562:31"/> live ſafely, or at all, without continual ſupply of food convenient for them.</p>
            <p>What fearefull trifling is this in a buſineſſe of ſuch high Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment! Good <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> when <hi>his heart was</hi> once <hi>lift up in the wayes of the Lord,</hi> tooke other order: for, hee ſent not only ſome of the prime <hi>Levites</hi> and <hi>Prieſts,</hi> who <hi>taught in Iudah and had the Booke of the Law of the Lord with them, and went about through all the Cities of Iudah and taught the people,</hi> 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 17.8, 9. but with them he ſent divers of his <hi>Princes and chiefe Officers, Benhail, Obadiah,</hi> and ſundry others, to ſee that this work ſhould be effectually done, <hi>verſe.</hi> 7. yea (as our late Tranſlation hath it) <hi>he ſent to them to teach in the Cities of Iudah:</hi> that is, that they ſhould take as much care of the buſines, by putting on the Prieſts and Levites, as if they themſelves in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon were bound to do all the worke. And hence it was, that God gave this teſtimony of <hi>Iehoſhaphat,</hi> that <hi>he walked in the firſt wayes of his father David,</hi> verſ. 3. that <hi>he had riches and honour in abundance,</hi> verſ. 5. and that <hi>the feare of the Lord fell upon all the Kingdomes of the Land round about Iudah, ſo that they made no warre againſt IEHO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHAPHAT,</hi> Verſ. 10. So that, beſide the ſpirituall benefit, a Preaching Miniſtry is one of the beſt advantages to ſecure a State; it is (you ſee) not only an hedge, but <hi>walles and Bulwarks</hi> unto any Kingdome.</p>
            <p>And yet, as many of our blind guides and Idol Shepheards care not to erect Preaching where there is none, ſo doe they all they can to cheat and defraud thoſe of it who doe or would enjoy it, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by pulling it down where it is ſet up, and (to fill up the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of their wickedneſſe) glorying in it, when they have done; ſometimes by ſtriking out the teeth of it, that if men will needs preach, yet it ſhall be to little purpoſe; only a frigid, toothleſſe, ſapleſſe diſcourſe, never piercing deeper than the eare. If the Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher come home to convince the Conſcience of particula s that need reformation, (which yet was the old courſe, and ſhould be ſo ſtill) the Preacher is either derided as worthy of nothing but contempt, or elſe cenſured as indiſcreet, raſh, factious, and ſeditious.</p>
            <p>And leaſt men ſhould ſurfeit of Preaching, how be all Sermons, in the afternoones of the LORD'S Dayes, cryed downe, as the markes of Iudaizing Puritaniſme, and as a burden intolerable to the people!</p>
            <pb n="55" facs="tcp:65562:31"/>
            <p>Indeed, it is true, that when Authority firſt commanded the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternoones Sermon to be converted into <hi>Catechiſing,</hi> there was not only no hurt done, but a wiſe and needfull courſe preſcribed for the beſt edifying of popular Auditories. But as ſome have handled the matter, it is now become a great hinderance to edification. If a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter would carefully and ſolidly open the ſeverall heads of Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, confirme them by Scripture, and bring them home by ſome ſhort and familiar application moſt ſutable to vulgar eares and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacities; I hold it ſimply the moſt profitable exerciſe (at leaſt for one part of the day) that can bee ſet up for the increaſe of ſound knowledge and Piety: and pity it is that this is ſo much neglected. <hi>But this,</hi> ſay our new Maſters, <hi>is worſe than preaching.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they enjoyn all to keep only to the bare Queſtions and Anſwers of the <hi>Child's</hi> Catechiſme. And if any preſume to adde any expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition or inſtruction, hee is by ſome hurried from poſt to pillar, and cenſured as a pernitious Malefactor.</p>
            <p>And as they have thus thruſt all preaching (be it but Catecheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) out of the Church in the afternoones of the Lords Day, ſo have they ſhut divers able, godly, diſcreet Paſtors out of their own Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits on the weeke dayes, even in Populous Townes, where the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters were willing to beſtow their paines, (and ſo for many yeares with great fruit and comfort to the whole Country had done) <hi>gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis,</hi> for the refreſhing of many hungry Soules who had no preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home in their owne Pariſhes, and dare not ſtirre thence on the Lords day to ſeeke it abroad.</p>
            <p>Nay, ſome of your Cathedrall Men are come to that paſſe, that when any Sermon (ſuch as it is) is preached in the Cathedrall or Collegiate Church, no Sermon muſt then be preached in the Pariſh Church or Churches adjoyning, meerely to uphold the Pompe and State of the Greater Church, and for feare of leſſening the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditory, or diminiſhing the honour of the Preacher, (who many times deſerves little enough) whereas not a fourth part of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation (by this meanes defrauded of Preaching in the Pariſh Church) can poſſibly come within hearing, or ken of the Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drall Pulpit-man.</p>
            <p>O Beloved! are theſe, wayes to ſet forth Chriſt to the people for their ſalvation, to diſplay <hi>God</hi> in all his glorious Attributes and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and to bring them within view of the beauties and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65562:32"/> of God in his Covenant and Communion with his people, ſo as to draw them to a Covenant! Nay hence, hence it comes to paſſe that God is extremely diſhonoured, his Name blaſphemed, his day abominably prophaned, and his people runne headlong (like beaſts to the Shambles) by droves, to Popery, Anabaptiſme, Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſme, Atheiſme, and what not, that may caſt, and locke them under the hatches of everlaſting damnation.</p>
            <q>
               <l>—Quis talia fando,</l>
               <l>Temperet a lachrymis?—</l>
            </q>
            <p>I know that ſome of thoſe Step-fathers and hard-hearted Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, who bee indeed the chiefe (if not the only) cauſe of all this, bluſh not to attribute the daily falling off of multitudes from our Church, to over much Preaching: but this is as rationall, as was his mad opinion touching Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> that much <hi>learning had made him mad.</hi> Theſe are crying Abominations, that will cry as loud againſt you, as now they doe againſt the Authours of them, if you reforme them not.</p>
            <p>Wonder not at my length, and heate in this point. It is a matter of greateſt Conſequence, and of all other moſt proper for a Preacher to be zealous in. And give me leave to tell you, that this muſt bee put in the head of the Catalogue of your weightieſt Conſultations at this time, if you deſire ever to draw the people of this and the Adjacent Dominions into any Covenant and Communion with God, or to ſettle any thing for the good of your ſelves and countries.</p>
            <p>K. <hi>Iames</hi> indeed took commiſeration of the groſſe ignorance of multitudes in the North parts of this Kingdom, and ſent ſome Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers at his owne charge among them. A Pious and a Noble work! But what through the unſetled wandrings, idleneſſe, the ſuperficiall and unprofitable performances of ſome of theſe Preachers, and what through the ſupine negligence of ſome in Authority who ſhould have looked better to thoſe itinerary Miniſters; moſt of that labour and charge was little better than loſt. For, ſome of you know, that in no parts of the kingdome hath there been ſuch an increaſe of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, as in thoſe very Corners, where that ſleight meanes was uſed to reduce men from Popery.</p>
            <p>I beſeech you therefore by all the mercies of God, by all the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of Chriſt in ſhedding of his deereſt bloud for thoſe precious Soules, who now, even by thouſands and millions miſerably periſh
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65562:32"/> in their ignorance and ſinnes, that you would carefully reforme, or caſt out all idle, unſound, unprofitable, and ſcandalous Miniſters; and provide a ſound, godly, profitable and ſetled Preaching Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in every Congregation through the Land and the annexed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions; and, to take no leſſe care for their diligent and conſtant performance of their dutie both in life and Doctrine, as alſo for their liberall maintenance, (that may be ſtill capable of improvement, as the times grow harder, and commodities deerer) that both them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves who preach the Goſpell, and all theirs alſo may cheerefully and comfortably live of the Goſpell. And let us once ſee <hi>Zion built up,</hi> by your induſtry, <hi>in perfect beautie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, when you ſet upon this great buſineſſe of a <hi>Covenant,</hi>
               <note place="margin">6. When a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is to be made, do it with all the heart; and forget it not when it is made.</note> ſee that you doe it out of <hi>love</hi> to God, and with all your heart: elſe, it will come to nothing. If you would to <hi>Zion, your faces</hi> muſt be ſet, and ſetled <hi>thitherward.</hi> If you would make a <hi>Covenant,</hi> you muſt not be unwilling, afraid, aſhamed to be accounted ſuch <hi>Covenanters,</hi> but doe it with a ſteddy, open, undaunted countenance and reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. You muſt <hi>love the name of your God to be his ſervants, Iſay</hi> 56.6. You have ſeen how <hi>Aſa</hi> and all his kingdome did it; they both en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into Covenant, and they <hi>ſwore it, with all their heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Chro. 15.15.</note> 
               <hi>and ſought him with their whole deſire, and he was found of them, and gave them reſt round about.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus if you do, God ſhall be ſet up, Religion advanced, your grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances removed, you ſhall heare no more ſuch complainings in our ſtreets. All bleſſings ſhall follow, not your ſelves alone, but the whole Kingdome, in our King and his Government, in your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſultations and proceedings, in the publike, ſetled, and glorious Peace, and proſperity of both Church and State. The bleſſings of the Earth, in the Citie, the field, your bodies, poſterity, in all your goings out and commings in; The bleſſings of heaven in the means of Grace, the beginnings and growth in grace, the light of Gods countenance which is better than life; and, after all, even the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of both grace and glory in the full, cleare, and eternall fruition of God Himſelfe in the higheſt heavens, ſhall all compaſſe, and Crowne you for ever.</p>
            <p>Provided alwayes, that when once this Covenant is made, you take care that <hi>it never be forgotten,</hi> but heeded, minded, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; that as you cloſe with God, ſo you may alwayes continue with
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65562:33"/> him. Then ſhall this whole nation and the children which are yet unborne praiſe and bleſſe the Lord for ever for this Parliament, and your endeavours in it. But I feele my ſelfe ſpent, and therefore muſt deſiſt, yet with this hope, that my Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend fellow-labourer deſigned for the other part of this work, will begin where I leave, and ſet on with more ſtrength what my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is not able to performe.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed by <hi>T.B.</hi> for <hi>Philemon Stephens</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Meredith</hi> at the ſigne of the Golden Lion in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1641</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
